<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The gouernement of all estates, wherein is contayned the perfect way to an honest life gathered out of many learned authors, a boke right profitable for all estates, but especiallie for the trayning [and] bringing vp of the yonger sort: written in Latin by that excellent learned man Andreus Hesse, translated into Englishe.</title>
            <author>Schottennius, Hermannus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1566</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 130 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03082</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13207</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116007</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851224</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851224</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16492</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03082)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16492)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 710:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The gouernement of all estates, wherein is contayned the perfect way to an honest life gathered out of many learned authors, a boke right profitable for all estates, but especiallie for the trayning [and] bringing vp of the yonger sort: written in Latin by that excellent learned man Andreus Hesse, translated into Englishe.</title>
                  <author>Schottennius, Hermannus.</author>
                  <author>Baarland, Adriaan van, 1486-1538. aut</author>
                  <author>Bourman, Nicholas.</author>
                  <author>Hermann IV, Landgrave of Hesse and Archbishop of Cologne, d. 1508, attributed name. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[256] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Denham, for Thomas Hacket, and are to be solde at his shop in Lumbart streate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1566]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end by translator: N. Boorman.</note>
                  <note>"Howe a man may attaine to the chiefe pointes of Christianitie, or deduction of a Christian life" by Adriaan van Baarland has caption title on M8r.</note>
                  <note>The modern attribution to Archbishop Herman IV is erroneous; in the preface the authors of the 2 sections are identified as Hermannus Hessus (i.e H. Schottenius, called Hessus) and Adrianus (i.e H.C.) Barlandus. In the first section excerpts from Latin poets are rendered in English verse--STC.</note>
                  <note>Colophon varies: undated or dated. In this copy the colophon is undated.</note>
                  <note>Last leaf blank?.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-Q R⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16492:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16492:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Gouernement of <hi>all estates, wherein is</hi>
               </hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the perfect way <hi>to an honeſt life, gathered out of</hi> many learned Authors, a boke <hi>right profitable for all eſtates, but</hi> eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peciallie for the trayning &amp; bringing vp of the yonger ſort: written in Latin by that excellent lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man <hi>Andreus Heſse,</hi> Tranſlated into Engliſhe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRINTED at London by Henry Denham,</hi> for Thomas Hacket, and <hi>are to be ſolde at his Shop</hi> in Lumbart ſtreate.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:16492:2"/>
            <head>N. B. In prayſe of this booke</head>
            <l>WHoſe ſteps do traine to taſt the ſweet</l>
            <l>&amp; pleaſant water ſpring:</l>
            <l>Incumbent at the Muſes féete,</l>
            <l>to winne <hi>Minerues</hi> ring.</l>
            <l>Approch the fountain top and Well,</l>
            <l>the pleaſant flouds to gaine:</l>
            <l>Of <hi>Hellyco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> wher Nymphes do dwel,</l>
            <l>and wiſedome hath the raigne.</l>
            <l>Imbrace with ioy hir darlings all</l>
            <l>that yéeldes to thée a crowne:</l>
            <l>With hand in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d through <hi>Pallas</hi> hall</l>
            <l>to foote it vp and downe.</l>
            <l>Here vertue ſhines, here ſiluer ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,</l>
            <l>here ſacred life hath place.</l>
            <l>Here <hi>Phoebus</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his gliſtring beames</l>
            <l>appeares with golden face.</l>
            <l>Here helth with welth, here quiet eaſe</l>
            <l>here ioy and frendſhip growes.</l>
            <l>Here medicines torned life to peaſe,</l>
            <l>here truth and honour flowes.</l>
            <l>Therefore as once before, come nie</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Sicilides</hi> doth call:</l>
            <l>And willing of thy companie,</l>
            <l>bids welcome to them all.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:16492:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Othing is more profitable in this world (gentle Reader) than ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt precepts, good counſels, worthie and godly perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, how to flée vice, and follow ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, which is the beſt and chiefeſt part of all Philoſophie, for by this meanes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealthes are maintained, the true limmit or direction of life freque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and all good &amp; godly families go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned. This meane the auncient Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours, or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcribed fathers of <hi>Rome</hi> with others in tymes paſt haue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, yea the Heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Poets &amp; Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers, alſo hauing taſted of the ſame. The ſcope of their whole workes doth tende to no other end, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of man, howe he ſhould vſe him ſelfe in modeſtie, counſelling him ſelfe in temperance, by practiſe, fortitude,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:3"/> and imitate iuſtice. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whiche is the touchſtone of all truth, that excellent Iewell of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and the bright Lantern of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritie, hath alſo taught vſ the way to all perfection of life, righteouſneſſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ctification. The principal meane aboue all others, whereby thou mayſt learne what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is at ſuch time as he liueth in the feare of God, &amp; wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vprightly in his calling. So all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being agréeable vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, may and ought to be enthraced as a guide or Rector of mans life vnto vertue, as this booke which is named the Gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of all eſtates, bicauſe it treateth of the trayning &amp; bringing vppe of man from his childhoode, or as <hi>Terence</hi> wryteth <hi>ex Ephoebis ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quam</hi> till his olde age, wherin ye may learne to attaine to the perfection of a probe or honeſt life. Firſt written in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine tongue by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> excellent man <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannus Heſsus,</hi> wherevnto is added the inſtitution of a Chriſtian man by <hi>Adrianus Barlandus,</hi> and now tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated
<pb facs="tcp:16492:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> into Engliſh, by thoſe who doe wiſh thy furtherance. Gentle Reader take this in good part, and in ſo doing thou ſhalt cauſe them to thinke their labours wel beſtowed, and encourage them to do greater things to thy god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly furtherance and profite: If that as mindfull of <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> thou accept their labour and momentarie practiſe: Hauing this conſideration, that as the Philoſopher requeſting of an old wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man the ſteppes of his paſſage, and ſhe by the aſſigning of hir finger declared the ſame, ſurrendred with a be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded knée thanks for hir demerits, then they (not yet requeſting ſo much curteſie) ſhal be the willinger, moued by this their induſtrie, to race or ingreſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſequence enterpriſe. Thus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting thée to the tuitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, I bid thée fare well.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale in Chriſto</salute>.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:16492:4"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To Babes and <hi>Sucklings.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>COme forth ye babes, learn now to trade</l>
            <l>your liues in liuing pure:</l>
            <l>Beholde the path of bliſſefull ſtate,</l>
            <l>good chaunce doth you aſſure.</l>
            <l>This little booke full tender yeares</l>
            <l>doth manifeſt and ſhow:</l>
            <l>How for to breake thoſe braunches yll</l>
            <l>that on ſuch grafts do grow.</l>
            <l>It doth declare the thing the which</l>
            <l>The Philoſophers olde,</l>
            <l>In wrytings graue to iudge for beſt,</l>
            <l>by reaſons law were bolde.</l>
            <l>What thing doth paſſe a mean, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame</l>
            <l>is counted worſt of all:</l>
            <l>What thing is beſt within a meane,</l>
            <l>the ſame doth neuer fall.</l>
            <l>Thus haue the wyſeſt counted it,</l>
            <l>and we the ſame ſuppoſe:</l>
            <l>This doth our filthie brutiſh life,</l>
            <l>to all mennes eyes diſcloſe.</l>
            <l>For none within a meane can kepe,</l>
            <l>it is a ſtate to baſe:</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:16492:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>We loue it well, but that it doth</l>
            <l>our euill life deface.</l>
            <l>It chaunced once <hi>Diogenes,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>in Market place to bée:</l>
            <l>Where as of men a great frequent</l>
            <l>he chaunced for to ſée.</l>
            <l>To whom aloude he cryed out,</l>
            <l>ye men come vnto me:</l>
            <l>The people then, what that he would,</l>
            <l>do runne ſtraight way to ſée.</l>
            <l>Suppoſing that he had ſome thing</l>
            <l>vnto them for to ſay:</l>
            <l>The which they him deſire forthwith,</l>
            <l>to them for to diſplay.</l>
            <l>He anſwered ſtraight I calde not you,</l>
            <l>but I for men did call:</l>
            <l>And ſure I am that not one man,</l>
            <l>there is among you all.</l>
            <l>And after that, beholding well</l>
            <l>a ſtripling yong to giue:</l>
            <l>Him ſelfe vnto Philoſofie,</l>
            <l>thereby to learne to liue.</l>
            <l>Well done (ꝙ he) thou calleſt thoſe,</l>
            <l>to puritie of minde:</l>
            <l>Whom carnall beautie w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hir ſleights</l>
            <l>indeuoured hath to blinde.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:16492:5"/>
            <l>Thus mayſt thou ſée what auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me</l>
            <l>accompted haue for beſt:</l>
            <l>And what in goodneſſe of this lyfe,</l>
            <l>ſurmounteth all the reſt.</l>
            <l>And as he hath deſerued, ſo</l>
            <l>rewarde him for his paine:</l>
            <l>Iudge right, firſt read, follow likewiſe</l>
            <l>hereby then ſhalt thou gaine.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS. J. P.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:16492:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>What an honeſt lyfe is,</hi> whereof it conſiſteth, and what profite ary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thereof.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The first Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eing therefore man was cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated into thys world, after all thynges were made, as lord &amp; ruler of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all,<note place="margin">Gene. 1.</note> &amp; appointed as Gods huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man here in earth, he ought ſo to direct the courſe of his life, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may pleaſe his <hi>Caeſar</hi> God, that by death being called into the Heauenly Pallace &amp; Court of his <hi>Caeſar</hi> (as kings and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were wonte to be called, of the humaine &amp; mortall <hi>Caeſars</hi>) may giue his acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of his good
<pb facs="tcp:16492:6"/> huſbandrie and gouernement. And leaſt he ſhould not be able to do this, he ought at al times to liue a noble, probable, and a Princely or honeſt life. And to leade an honeſt life is nothing elſe, than in conditions to differ from a bruite beaſte, and as much as by nature a man may to lyue moſte lyke vnto God, which conſiſteth in nothing els but in vertue, is to flie vice and follow honeſtie: for that is the office and ende of vertue. And that the honeſtie and the lyfe wherwith God is moſt pleaſed, doth conſiſt by Vertue, Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> teſtifieth, ſayng: <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem eſſe artem bene viuendi,</hi> that is, Vertue to be the art of well lyuing,<note place="margin">Mantua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</note> and alſo <hi>Baptiſta Mantua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nꝰ</hi> doth expreſſe with theſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des what vertue is, and howe
<pb facs="tcp:16492:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> great commodities it bringeth to man.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="poem">
                           <head>Virtutis querimonium.</head>
                           <l>I am dame fortunes Maiſtreſſe,</l>
                           <l>of vice the ſcourging rod:</l>
                           <l>My onely care and ſtudy is,</l>
                           <l>to bring man ſafe to God.</l>
                           <l>He that my doctrines learne will,</l>
                           <l>they ſhall perſuade him ſo:</l>
                           <l>To God and his Emperiall ſeate,</l>
                           <l>the right way for to go.</l>
                           <l>I am a ſigne directing ſtraight,</l>
                           <l>the middle way to go:</l>
                           <l>Wherin our auncient fathers ſteps,</l>
                           <l>are yet now for to ſhow.</l>
                           <l>By which they haue aſcended right,</l>
                           <l>the heauenly gates of God:</l>
                           <l>Where in moſt pleaſant ſmelling fiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</l>
                           <l>the milky floods haue flowde.</l>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>¶ <hi>Plutarch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> alſo expreſſeth more plainly, what vertue doth teach vs, deſcribing hir in his booke
<pb facs="tcp:16492:7"/> of the education of children, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the name and title of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophie, ſaying, that by hir it is to be deſcerned what is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, what is vnhoneſt, what is iuſt, and what is vniuſt, what ought to be imbraced, &amp; what ought vtterly to be eſchewed, how &amp; after what ſort we ought and ſhoulde behaue our ſelues towardes our Parents, our el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſtraungers and pilgrims, our gouernors &amp; Magiſtrates, our frendes, our wyues, chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and families, and that we ſhould worſhip GOD, honour our parents, reuerence our el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, obey our Princes lawes, giue place and ſubmit our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to our Superiours, and with all oure heartes to loue oure friendes as oure ſelues. Women to brydle the ſnaffle
<pb facs="tcp:16492:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> of ill concupiſence, euer to haue care and reſpecte to their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens education, not to be in bondage, or conſent with their ſeruaunt, &amp; that which is chiefe of all, neither to reioyce to much in proſperitie, neyther to be to contriſt and ſad in aduerſitie, neyther to haue any voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous appetyte or deſyre at all. And ſo to repreſſe coler and ire, that we become not like brutiſh beaſtes, whoſe nature and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition is alwaye to be fearce and vngentle, but as men diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete, whoſe nature is to be meeke, lowly and gentle.</p>
               <p>Secondarilie,<note place="margin">Tullie.</note> 
                  <hi>Tullie</hi> in hys firſt boke of Offices ſayth, that there be foure Wel ſprings and originall fountaines of vertue, from whiche all other diſcende, and oute of which all honeſtie
<pb facs="tcp:16492:8"/> procedeth, which be theſe, Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Iuſtice, Temperaunce, and fortitude, which foure haue foure ſeuerall and dyuers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and nature as <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crob.</hi> teſtifieth in his boke <hi>de ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio Scipionis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Macrob. de ſomnio Scipionis.</note> who expreſſeth their qualities in this wyſe, ſaying: it belongeth to a prudent man, to knowe and forecaſt howe to compaſſe eche matter and caſe, neyther to doe nor deſire ought elſe, but iuſtice and equitie, to contriue his humaine and worldly affayres, with a godly and diuine minde, to prouide and puruey againſt damages and daungerous haps, whiche by caſualties might chaunce or happen.</p>
               <p>The point and ende of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude is, not to feare loſſe and detriments, to feare onely wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<pb facs="tcp:16492:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> and vngodly thinges, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly and with pacient ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, to forſake proſperity and aduerſity. Fortitude is of more price tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magnanimitie, faith, conſtancie, fecuritie, magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, pacience, and ſtableneſſe.</p>
               <p>The qualitie of Temperance is not to ſay after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dede done, had I wiſt, in al affayres to vſe wit and diſcretion, and vnder the rule of reaſon to brydle ill co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcence of the fleſh, whoſe handemaydes are modeſtie, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, abſtinence, chaſtitie, honeſtie, moderation, frugality, ſobrietie, and ſhamefaſtneſſe.</p>
               <p>The poynt and propertie of Iuſtice, is to reſtore to euerye man his right &amp; duetie, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſcend innocencie, frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip, concord, pietie, religion, neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borly affection, and humanitie,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:9"/> 
                  <hi>Cicero in officiis</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Cicero in officiis.</note> that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould hurte his neighbour, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he had ſuſtayned wrong before. Secondly, to vſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon as common, and his owne as his owne. The true foundation and roote wherof is fayth, that is, conſtancie and truth in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and dedes.<note place="margin">Lactan. lib. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his ſixt booke ſayth, that there are two offices and dueties of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, wherof the firſt participate with God by Religion, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde with man by compaſſion and gentle behauiour.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Macrobiꝰ</note>By theſe vertues ſayth <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crobius,</hi> a good man ruleth hym ſelfe and his houſholde, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently, the publike weale, vprightlye maintayning hys worldely affayres.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>¶ The reward of vertuous and honeſt life.</head>
                  <p>IF any man be inquiſitiue of the office and reward of Vertue and honeſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, he muſt knowne that there belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth two properties to it. Firſt, to inryche man with the tranſitorie riches of thys worlde, and after death to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him with euerlaſting ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation which neuer ſhall haue ende.<note place="margin">Virgilius.</note> Whervpon <hi>Virgill</hi> wryteth well, ſaying: there are but few whome vpright <hi>Iupiter</hi> with a ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t zeale fauoured, or whom Vertue extolleth to the highe heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or elſe according to <hi>Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantius</hi> in his ſixt booke:<note place="margin">Lactan. lib. 6.</note> It is the propertie of Vertue to refraine anger, to aſſwage gredy appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites, and to brydle carnall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires.
<pb facs="tcp:16492:10"/> Secondly, Vertue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth hir ſcholer and Client, the true rycheſt man aboue all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in ſo muche that he ſhall want nothing, but ſhall haue aboundance of euery thing. As <hi>Plato in Amph.</hi> writeth thus,<note place="margin">Plato in Amph.</note> that Vertue leadeth the waye, and ſheweth the pathe to all things perfectly. And libertie, health, life, ſubſtance, parents, &amp; kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes defende and garde hir.</p>
                  <p>Vertue poſſeſſeth all things within hir ſelfe, the vertuous man lacketh nothing, but he hath all things at will, who ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth by Vertue.</p>
                  <p>For vertue is not deſirous of common prayſe, neyther of that which euery man alloweth, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther requireth ſhe honor, or glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye,<note place="margin">Sillius.</note> as the Poet <hi>Silius</hi> ſayth. <hi>Ipſa quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> virtus ſibimet pulcherrima mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> Vertue is a beautifull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde to it ſelfe.<note place="margin">Claudius.</note> Vnto whome the Poet <hi>Claudius</hi> agreeth in theſe verſes.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ipſa quidem virtus precium ſibi, ſola<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>, latè</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fortunae ſecura nitet: nec faſcibus vllis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Erigitur planſuue petit clareſcere vulgi</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nil opis externae cupiens, nil indiga laudis,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diuitijs animoſa ſuis, immota<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>, cunctis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſibus, ex alta mortalia deſpicit arce.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Virtutis repulſae neſcia ſordidae</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Horatius.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Intaminatis fulget honoribus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>Vertue is great in euery wyght,</l>
                     <l>where ſhe doth beare the ſway:</l>
                     <l>Not obfuſcat, by dimmend light,</l>
                     <l>but fayrer than the day.</l>
                     <l>An honour bright, a Caſtle ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>and tower of defence:</l>
                     <l>To tende and preace thy foes among,</l>
                     <l>to winne a recompence.</l>
                     <l>Therefore indeuour vertuouſly</l>
                     <l>this vertue for to holde:</l>
                     <l>A ſparke of ſuch royaltie,</l>
                     <l>as paſſeth yellow golde.</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:11"/>
                  <p>Neither doth the Lady Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue deſire ryches or worldlye goodes for any reward: for ſhe farre excelleth them all, and is much more noble and precious than they, as <hi>Horace</hi> teſtifieth by this verſe.<note place="margin">Horatius.</note> 
                     <hi>Vilius argentum eſt auro, virtutibus aurum.</hi> Syluer is courſer mettell than golde, and golde courſer than Vertue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Macrob. de ſomnio Scipionis.</note>Wherevpon <hi>Macrobius</hi> in his booke <hi>de Somnio Scipionis</hi> ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a wyſe man attributeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruite and reward of his vertue to his wiſdom: for he is no right per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect wiſe man, which onely ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth for ambition and glorye. And in the ſame place he wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, that who ſo deſireth to be a perfect vertuous man, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent his gredy appetite with re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde of his knowledge, that is, that he be content that he
<pb facs="tcp:16492:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> knoweth Vertue, &amp; not to ſeeke the vaine glory thereof.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ How to lead an honeſt and vertuous lyfe.</head>
               <head>¶ The ſecond Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hoſoeuer deſyreth to lyue an honeſt &amp; vertuous lyfe, he muſte obſerue two neceſſary poyntes. Firſt, that he prepare his mind, whereby he may become wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of vertue and honeſtie. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condlye, that (his minde thus prepared) he ſeeke and ſearche out, howe and by what meanes he maye attayne vnto Vertue. The preparation of the minde, muſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed by thre things that is, by a willing &amp; prompt deſyre, that his deſire be to will
<pb facs="tcp:16492:12"/> that he profite in vertue, for it is a great help to honeſty, to haue a deſire to become honeſt: for there is nothing ſo difficulte, which may not be compriſed by a willing minde, ſo is there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing harder, than to make an vnwilling perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> willing, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ryſeth this Prouerbe, <hi>Stul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt, canes inuitos ducere venatum,</hi> It is a fond thing, to make vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing houndes hunt, that is, to compell a nilling man to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny kinde of labour is in vaine, wherefore <hi>Cornicus</hi> ſayth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſo eaſye but maye be made vneaſie, if thou do it with an vnluſtie minde. <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his firſte booke <hi>de inſtit. chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lactan. lib. 1. de inſtit. Chriſti.</note> ſayeth, that Vertue it ſelfe oughte to be adored, and not the Image of Vertue. And it ought not be worſhipped
<pb facs="tcp:16492:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> with any ſacrifyce, oblations, frankincenſe, or ſolemne ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but wholly with a volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarye and determined minde. And the minde thus deſirous and ſtirred to ſeke vertue, muſt moreouer be ſuffulced and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected with two other precepts whiche are patience and abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, that it ſuſtaine, ſuffer, &amp; abide much paine and trauaile, and withdrawe affection from all thinges, and eſpecially from things voluptuous.</p>
               <p>Who ſo doth feruentlye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre vertue, muſt be very patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and much ſuffering, that he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide and beare the burthen of aduerſitie, and the payne of his labour quietly, that he ſuffer aduerſitie.<note place="margin">Virgilius. Aened. 6.</note> And as <hi>Virgil</hi> ſayth in his ſixt booke of <hi>Eneidos. Non cedat malis,</hi> Giue not place, nor
<pb facs="tcp:16492:13"/> be moued with any miſſehap or chaunce: but boldely, manly, &amp; ſtoutly, withſtande and reſiſte the ſame. For as <hi>Valerius</hi> in hys ſixt booke ſayth:<note place="margin">Valerius. lib. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Euernos animos virtus odiſſe ſolet.</hi> Vertue doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne &amp; adnihilate the weake and feble minds: that is to ſay, Vertue doth hate &amp; enuie thoſe greatly, whiche be of fearefull mindes, which dare not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe any thing, and which alſo vſe no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancy in their doings. Moreouer, to proue patience and abſtinence guides &amp; tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers to ſeeke vertue, <hi>Horace</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clareth playnely in theſe verſes following.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Horatius.</note>
                     <hi>Qui ſtudet optatam curſu contingere metam,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Multa tulit, fecit<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, puer, ſudauit &amp; alſit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Abſtinuit venere &amp; Baccho.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Who ſo hath inclinde him ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>to hit the wiſhed marke:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>His childiſh yeres haue ſuffered much</l>
                  <l>and eke compiled much worke.</l>
                  <l>In burning heate, in pinching colde,</l>
                  <l>his time he hath conſumde:</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Venus</hi> ſports &amp; <hi>Bacchus</hi> chéere</l>
                  <l>him ſelfe he hath amoude.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prudentius</hi> alſo that Chriſtian Poet,<note place="margin">Pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuis.</note> doth declare in theſe ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes following, howe that paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence muſte nedes be the way and guide to him that ſeketh to Vertue.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Omnibus vna comes virtutibus aſsociatur:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Auxilium<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſuum fortis patientia miſcet.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nulla anceps luctame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> init, virtute ſine iſta:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>virtus na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vidua eſt, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patientia firmat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Deſine grande loqui, fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>git deus o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſuperbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Magna cadu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, inflata crepa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, tumefacta pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Diſce ſupciliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deponere, diſce cauere</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ante pedes fouea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quiſquis ſublime minaris.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Peruulgati viget noſtri ſententia Cbristi</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dere celſa humilis et ad ima reddere vora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>If trauail thine do race and tende</l>
                  <l>the vertuous ſteps to gaine.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:14"/>
                  <l>To pacience lore thy ſtudy bende,</l>
                  <l>aſſociate thou hir traine.</l>
                  <l>Permit a tyme, forbeare for eaſe,</l>
                  <l>proude mindes to ruine fall:</l>
                  <l>Let humbleneſſe thy fury peaſe,</l>
                  <l>the voyce of Chriſt doth call.</l>
               </q>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Abſtinence.</head>
                  <p>ANd many ſkilful Clarks haue approued alſo Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> petula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cious deſires &amp; voluptuous affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be very nedeful to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeker of Vertue,<note place="margin">Cicero nouae rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. lib. 4.</note> as <hi>Cicero lib. 4 nouae Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoricae,</hi> ſaith. <hi>Qui nihil in vita habet iucundius vita voluptuaria, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> virtute vitam colere non poteſt.</hi> He that in hys lyfe eſtemeth nor regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth nothing more than hys volupiuous and wanton lyfe, can not inhabit with Vertue. And alſo <hi>Valerius Maximꝰ</hi> in his fourth boke ſaith:<note place="margin">Valerius. Maximus lib. 4.</note> That Citie whoſe Inhabitants are moſt
<pb facs="tcp:16492:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t delights, loſeth hir Empire and dominion, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can that Citye kepe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende hir owne liberty and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but contrarywiſe, that Citie whoſe Inhabitours doe wholly incline them ſelues to labour, doth rule and is able to giue libertie and fredom to others.<note place="margin">Lactan. lib. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>Lactantius</hi> alſo in hys ſixt booke wryteth, that there be three kindes of Vertues. Wherof the firſt is to refraine euill factes &amp; nefarious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes: the ſeconde is to tye thy tongue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſclaundering, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byting and obſerious talking, the thirde is, to expell all euill, wicked, and malicious cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, thoughtes and preme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations from out thy minde. He that followeth the firſt, is a vertuous man. He that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:16492:15"/> the ſecond, is a perfect ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous man, if ſo be that he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende neither by worde nor by deede. And he that followeth the thirde, followeth the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: for it is aboue humaine nature to paſſe the cogitation therof, which ſhould neither be nequitious to be done, or vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to be ſpoken. Therfore he that ſeketh vertue, muſt nedes vſe the helpe of pacience and abſtinence. By whoſe helpe &amp; ayde he may beare and abide aduerſe, fortune and greate labour quietly, abhorre ydle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and imbrace ſweate and labour.<note place="margin">Heſiodus.</note> For <hi>Heſiodus</hi> the Poet ſayth, that the Gods haue pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Vertue in the highe, and alte places, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he which woulde winne hir, ſhould ſeke hir with much ſweat, and grieuous tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell.
<pb facs="tcp:16492:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> For which conſideration many Philoſophers haue ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t much more Oyle than Wyne, haue ſuffred muche ſweate, and haue but little or nothing at all giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them ſelues to idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for idleneſſe debilitateth and weakeneth vertue, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwyſe, labour vpholdeth &amp; ſufficeth hir. And abſtenence is alſo very neceſſarye, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtayne from vicious liuing. For Vertue, as <hi>Horace</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Horatius.</note> is nothing elſe but a ſecluder of vice.</p>
                  <p>And when as thou haſt thus inſtructed and prepared thy minde, that is with a volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie will, with pacience and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, then muſt thou ſeeke &amp; inquire of the learned bokes and monumentes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> famous Clearkes, which is the way to
<pb facs="tcp:16492:16"/> afcende vnto Vertue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, for they teach and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulgat, and eſpecially <hi>Laertius</hi> in his booke <hi>de vitis Philoſophoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Laertius de vitis Philoſo.</note> that eche doctrine requireth thre things, which are, nature, inſtruction, and vſe, that is to ſay, wit, learning, and exerciſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Theſe thrée are nedefull to Vertue.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt a ſharpe wit whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and not blunt as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                     <hi>Beotians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plato.</note> for <hi>Plato</hi> ſayth, that none can be perfect wyſe, that is to ſay perfect vertuous, vnleſſe he excell in witte and knowledge, and be imbewed, and adorned with the comely partes of prudence. As many Philoſophers as we read ther were in olde tyme, they did all excell in the capacitie of witte.
<pb facs="tcp:16492:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> Herevpon <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his firſte booke ſayth,<note place="margin">Lactan. lib. 1.</note> that there are two kindes of wiſdome: whereof the firſt is to diſcerne which be falſe, the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to know which be true. For all vnderſtanding and knowledge conſiſteth of a polyſhed, that is to ſay a quick and ſharpe witte:<note place="margin">Lactantiꝰ lib. 2.</note> Alſo <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> in his ſeconde booke ſayth, that they doe expell and carye away wiſdome from them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, which without any iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments before had, allowe the inuentions of their elders, and are led and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>duced of others, as brute beaſtes, wherfore wit is nedefull and very neceſſary, both to ſearch vertue, and alſo to iudge other mens workes. <hi>Cicero</hi> in his <hi>Tuſculans</hi> queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſayth:<note place="margin">Cicero Queſti. Tuſcul.</note> 
                     <hi>Ingenio noſtro innata ſunt ſemina quaedem virtutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp;c.</hi> By
<pb facs="tcp:16492:17"/> our witte, there be certaine ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of vertue ſprong vp, which if they might be ſuffered to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, nature hir ſelfe woulde bring &amp; conduct vs to a bleſſed life. If therefore certaine ſedes of vertue are ſprong vp by our wit, certaine it is, that the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues them ſelues haue their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginall of wit, as from a trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury or ſtorehouſe therof. And euen by witte euery man doth either ſeke vertues, or elſe doth conceyue and learne them the better of his teacher. In conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration wherof, the auncient &amp; graue Philoſophers woulde neuer at any time receyue any as their ſcholers, before they had ſcrupulouſlye ſought oute his witte and ingene, and if he were dull and not fine witted, they woulde deny to inſtructe
<pb facs="tcp:16492:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> him. For <hi>Quintilian</hi> ſayth.<note place="margin">Quintili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus.</note> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts profite the dul wittes no more, than tillage the ſterill &amp; barren field, which be it neuer ſo well tilled, will neuer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe or edure any fruite at al. Yet ought he not to diſpaire whome God hath not ſente ſo pregna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t a wit, but endeuer by continuall labour and paines, to ſlip away at length all that hardeneſſe and infertilitie of his witte,<note place="margin">Quintil. lib. 1. ca. 1.</note> as <hi>Quintilian</hi> ſayth in his firſt booke and firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. One man excelleth an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in witte, but ſo that he can do either more or leſſe. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe there is none, but that by his labour &amp; induſtrie, may at length become ingenious. And though that ech man can not excell, yet muſt he not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leue to proue, for as <hi>Horace</hi>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:18"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:19"/> ſayth:<note place="margin">Horatius.</note> 
                     <hi>Eſt quodda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prodire tenus, ſi no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> datur vltra.</hi> It is ſomewhat to go as farre as thou can, if thou may goe no further, that is to ſay: he is worthy prayſe which maketh but a ſmall iourney, if that the rudeneſſe of his wytte let him from going forwards. Yet betwixt the witty and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witty there is a double diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. Firſte, the witty of his owne accord and with a ſwift courſe, conſecuteth and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vertue, euen as a prouoked horſe to ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne his courſe, which muſt be retired with bridle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. And the dull witted is like a horſe which can not be dryuen to runne, without ofte ſpurring: ſo that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> obtuſe wit is to be whetted ſharpe wyth paynefull labours.<note place="margin">Quintil.</note> And <hi>Quinti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> ſheweth here, how <hi>Iſocrates</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> had two ſcholers, <hi>Ephorus,</hi> and <hi>Theopopus,</hi> the one wittie, who ſayth he lacked a brydle to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre him, the other dul, who he ſayth lacked ſpurres to kicke him forwardes. The ſeconde difference is, how that the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and pregnant witte conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth not noble for a long ſpace, or elſe by obliuion forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth that it hath learned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. As the ſoone rype Apples are alwayes ſoone rotten, but the harde Winter Apples doe molifie and rype more leyſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and therefore they endure and continue the longer: ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hard and obtuſe wit, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of time and exerciſe, is made worthye and fitte for vertue. For <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Eraſmus.</note> that by daylye practiſe wittes doe molifie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:20"/>
                  <head>¶ Of diſcipline, ſcience, or inſtruction.</head>
                  <p>AND when as thus thou haſt made ſharpe &amp; whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thy wit, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haſt thou nede of ſcience or inſtruction, for neyther doeth nature nor witte ſuffiſe onely, vnleſſe they be aſſociate with inſtruction. bycauſe that it maketh that perfect, which elſe by nature is vnperfect.<note place="margin">Cicero nouae rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. lib. 3.</note> Therefore <hi>Cicero</hi> in his thirde booke intituled <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Rethorica,</hi> ſayth: that ſcience doth confirme, ſtabliſhe and augment the commodities of nature, and in the fourth boke of the ſame Rethoricke <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth.<note place="margin">Ibid. lib. 4</note> 
                     <hi>Vt equus indomitus, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uis bene natura compoſitus ſit, idoneus no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poteſt eſſe ad eas vtilitates et artes, quae deſiderantur ab equo, ita neque homo
<pb facs="tcp:16492:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> indoctus, quamuis ingenioſus, ad vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutem poteſt peruenire, quoniam non poteſt virtus ſine doctrina comparari.</hi> Euen as an vntamed horſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his proporcion be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo well ſhapen and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pact by the art nature, can not be made fitte and apt for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities and feates which are deſired in a horſe: no more ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an vnlerned man, be he neuer ſo wittie, aſcende vnto Vertue, bycauſe that vertue can not be adopted or obtayned without learning. Vpon this, the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Gentiles erected common ſcholes, firſt at <hi>Athens</hi> a Citie of the Grecians moſt excellent &amp; famous, and at that tyme in many other places, that in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, youth might be educated and inſtructed in knoweledge, and in comelye, decent and honeſt
<pb facs="tcp:16492:21"/> maners, which two are but ſic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerly gotten without inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Therefore <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> the Philoſopher did compare the vnlearned, rude, &amp; vntaught, to a hard ſtone, of whom a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine olde father inquired at a certaine tyme, what profite or commoditie he ſhoulde doe to his ſonne, if he ſhoulde bring him vp in learning, he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>Si nihil aliud, ſaltem in theatro non ſedebit lapis ſuper lapidem, non erit apud doctos tanquam lapis.</hi> If it profiteth him nothing, yet at leaſt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſitteth beholding any theatre and worthy thing one ſtone ſitteth not on an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, neyther ſhall he be as a ſtone dumbe without ſpeache, when as he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth in the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pany of the learned. The <hi>Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nickes</hi> did knowe that Vertue
<pb facs="tcp:16492:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> was to be gotten by inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In conſideration wherof, they kepte ſcholemaſters or inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters at home, vnder whoſe rule and gouernement their chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren learned Artes and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. And that was ſo religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous amongſt the <hi>Athenia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s,</hi> that they ordeyned a law, that their children ſhould not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned nor coerced to nouriſhe their aged fathers, vnles their fathers in their youth had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted them to mayſters to be inſtructed and brought vp in the knowledge of Vertue. And inſtruction to attayne Vertue by, is two fold: the one is mute and dombe, the other quicke &amp; liuelye. The mute and dombe is, to be learned by the bookes and monumentes of the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned wryters, by the reading of
<pb facs="tcp:16492:22"/> which, we are taught without any worde ſpeaking. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quicke and liuely inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is to be lerned at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſchole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, who from their liuely mouth, doe ſende and infunde into the eares of yong me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the precepts of Vertue. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the liuely inſtruction excelleth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mute. For we reade y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> therfore many Philoſophers trauailed many cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treys, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther left they any vnſeene, as <hi>Pyhatgoras, Empedocles, Democritus,</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> occupied &amp; vſed naui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very oft, to obtaine ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by that moſte amiable Ladye Vertue, and with their peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and long iourneys, they ſought hir out curiouſly: for they could not be conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted nor ſatiſfyed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhadowed, &amp; candle dropped ſtudy, which
<pb facs="tcp:16492:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> they might haue had betwixte two walles, but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferred them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues thether where any wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy thing was to bee learned, not bookes, but perfite and ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Philoſophers or inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours. There are foure kinde of bookes of Authours princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally to be reade, which be the workes of Poets wryting honeſtly, the painefull labours of Hiſtoriographers, the wyſe, diſcrete and ſage ſayings of Philoſophers, and the deuine ſenſe of ſacred ſcripture. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Poetes doe ſo much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct and lead to an honeſt life, that the moſt famous and ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Cities of the Greekes in tyme paſte, did bring vp and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducate their children, firſte in Poetes, affirming Poetes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be wyſe, ſage and ſeuere.
<pb facs="tcp:16492:23"/> In Poets, children are taught Vertue, as <hi>Horace</hi> ſayth in his Epiſtles moſt truly.<note place="margin">Horatius.</note>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Os purum tenerum, balbum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, Poeta figurat:</l>
                     <l>Mox etiam pectus preceptis format amicis,</l>
                     <l>Inſtruit exemplis, inopem ſolatur, &amp; egrum.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>The tender ſtutting childiſhe mouth,</l>
                     <l>the Poet ſhapes aright:</l>
                     <l>And then with frendly precepts doth,</l>
                     <l>the heart and breaſt adight.</l>
                     <l>With good examples doth he then</l>
                     <l>inſtruct the childiſhe boy:</l>
                     <l>He comfortes eke the nedy men.</l>
                     <l>whom ſickneſſe doth anoy.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Secondly, the worthy Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographers which declare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs the famous geſtes, ciuill maners, and happy fortunes of noble and worthy men, by whoſe laudable lyfe we may ſe the way of well lyuing, and by whoſe temeritie or vnlucky de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinie, we maye foreſee to lyue
<pb facs="tcp:16492:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> more circumſpectly, which is a goodlye thing, to vſe others raſhneſſe to our temperance, as <hi>Diodorus</hi> ſayth:<note place="margin">Diodorus</note> It is a faire thing by other mens faults to amende our owne maculous lyfe, and by the example of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to knowe what is to be deſired, and what is to be eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chewed. An Hiſtorie, ſayth <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roaldus,</hi> doth greatly profyte,<note place="margin">Beroaldus</note> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that that is honeſt, deteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and adnihilating the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, extolling the ſincere and godly, ſuppreſſing the peruers and wretched. Thirdely, the bookes of the milde Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, which declare and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme vs of the documentes and precepts of Vertue, as the ten bookes of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> intituled his Ethicke, <hi>Ciceros</hi> thrée boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of Offices, <hi>Lactantius</hi> works
<pb facs="tcp:16492:24"/> 
                     <hi>de deuina inſtitut. Eraſmus</hi> of the inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Prince, &amp; manie mo, which haue liuely, vertuouſly &amp; frendly depainted and ſette forth the trade of an honeſt lyfe. Fourthly and laſt of all, the bookes of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which declare and teach, howe we ſhoulde knowe God, whom to know a creator of all thinges, and he to be but one onely, is the dere, true and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte wiſdome of man,<note place="margin">Lactantiꝰ lib. 2.</note> as <hi>Lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantius</hi> wryteth in his ſeconde booke.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Pouertie ought not to be repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to Vertue.</head>
                  <p>IT is not to be eſteemed that manye accuſe and conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne pouertie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they can leſſe apply the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Vertue. For as <hi>Apuleius</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſayth, pouertie was in old time houſe ſeruant to the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, neither was any know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en to aſcende to any dignitie, whome pouertie had not enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tried and brought vp, euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy. Pouertie in aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient tyme was conditrix and edificatrix of all Cities, the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour and guide of al artes, cleare of all faultes, the liberal rewarder of all prayſe, whome all nations haue extolled and magnificenced with all prayſe and glory. Therefore <hi>Apuleius</hi> ſayth thus, if any man be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed with pouertie, let him imitate <hi>Cleantes,</hi> a Philoſopher, who conſtrained through po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie labored by night, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing water, to the intente that he mighte prouide for to buye his victuall fode in the day, by
<pb facs="tcp:16492:25"/> which meanes, he mighte the more commodiouſly apply hys ſtudy: let him therfore labour while time is, that he may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliat whereby to liue and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne Vertue, which commeth vnto the paynefull labourers hande.<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> Whervpon <hi>Seneca</hi> ſayth thus. <hi>Virtute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Templo inuenies, in Foro, in Curia, per muros ſtante<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerulentam, colorata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, calloſas habente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, manꝰ, qui nihil aliud videtur oſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dere, quam quod etiam laborioſos homines virtus adiuuat &amp; amplectitur.</hi> Thou ſhalt finde vertue in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in the Market place, in the Court, ſtanding before the walles all duſtie, al to be pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with durte, hauing harde handes, wherby it is to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued, that Vertue doth alſo loue and imbrace laborious men.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>¶ Whether Vertue can be adopted without learning.</head>
                  <p>IN caſe adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ſome would ſay, there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vnlerned men which neuer at any tyme adhibited their mindes to ſtudy, and yet are reputed and eſtemed men of an honeſt lyfe and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. It is to be aunſwered: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as ſome aſcend vnto Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue by their ſinguler wit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out learning,<note place="margin">Cicero de oration.</note> as <hi>Cicero</hi> in his booke of Orations teſtifieth, ſaying: I haue knowen many notable wittie men, vertuous, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out learning, who haue bene by nature modeſt and graue. And this alſo doe I often aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe vnto Vertue: nature to be of muche more excellencye without learning, than lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:16492:26"/> without nature. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, euen the ſame I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tend, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as, eloquence &amp; the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of learning is ioyned with an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and noble nature, then do I not know what ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue egregious &amp; notorious. This ſpake <hi>Cicero</hi> verye pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of excerciſe and practiſe.</head>
                  <p>YEt beſide witte and ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, thirdely he muſt vſe the helpe of exercyſe, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe he ſtudieth friuolouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſeeke Vertue.<note place="margin">Cicero nouae rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. lib. 3.</note> As <hi>Cicero</hi> teſtifieth in his thirde booke of newe Rethoricke. <hi>In omni diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plina infirma eſt artis praeceptio ſine ſumma aſſiduitate excitationis, tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro in memoriis minimum valet doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trina niſi induſtria &amp; labore, &amp; dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia comprebetur.</hi> In euery diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline
<pb facs="tcp:16492:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> the precept of Art is feble and of no force, vnleſſe it be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulouſly exerciſed. And alſo doctrine preuayleth nothing in memorie, except with great induſtrie, labour and diligence it be proued.<note place="margin">Lactan. lib. 3.</note> And <hi>Lactantius</hi> in his thirde boke ſayth, that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes are therefore learned, not that they ſhuld be only knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alſo exerciſed, &amp; that they ſhoulde be vſed eyther for the helpe of mans lyfe, or for plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, or elſe for glory and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy fame.<note place="margin">Cicero in officiis.</note> 
                     <hi>Cicero</hi> in his booke of Offices ſayth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al the prayſe of vertue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth not in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Vertue, but in the function thereof, that is, it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileth but litle to know what Vertue is, what is honeſt, and what is vicious, but to vſe and exerciſce vertue it ſelfe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>¶ How that this exerciſe of the ſcience which thou knoweſt or haſt, had, is the way to get vertue.</head>
                  <p>WHo ſo deſireth the fruit and commodity of true Vertue and ſincere ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, out of thoſe .iiij. bokes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay, of Poetrie, Hiſtorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphie, Philoſophie, and holy Scripture, it is neceſſarie he learne the accuſtomed maner of Bees in the collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their honie. The Bees are accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med when as they gather ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, to flie about diuers floures, to taſt many floures, and of the iuyce thereof to excerpe &amp; ſucke ſomewhat, and then to carye ſome of the moyſture thereof in to their Hyues, which they lay downe and fardel vp together, to compound hony therof: thus
<pb facs="tcp:16492:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> frequenting and doyng this often, they conſerue and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merate muche hony on heapes in length of tyme, which is a ſweete fruite of their labours: euen ſo muſte the deſirous to be vertuous, which alſo wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth to come to the ſtate of a man, vſe a quadruple exerciſe.</p>
                  <p>The firſt exerciſe is, that he excerpate &amp; annote in a voide booke, as the keper of memory, whatſoeuer he ſhal reade or be taught, which mai be a furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to eloquence and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. For an egregious man muſt haue the vſe of them both as <hi>Cicero</hi> teſtifieth in his fyrſte booke of his olde Rhetoricke, affirming that wiſdome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out eloquence helpeth little to the gouernment of Cities, and eloquence withoute wiſdome
<pb facs="tcp:16492:28"/> doth hinder more than profite. Let euery Student therefore, make him two voyde bookes, in which he ſhall wryte both what he hath heard, and alſo what he hath read: in the one to annote fine ſugred ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in other vertuous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, like a couetous man, who heapeth vp treaſures, for which he hath dyuers cheſtes, ſpecially where he putteth his ſiluer, &amp; where he putteth his golde, alone. This exerciſe did <hi>Plinie</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſitor of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Hiſtory, vſe and imitate, of whom <hi>Plinie</hi> his ſeconde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle wryteth, that he neuer read any thing worthy to be noted, but he comitted it to writing. The ſecond exerciſe is, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale ſuch annotations in the retentiue memorie, and that
<pb facs="tcp:16492:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> he thinke to vſe them often as <hi>Macrobius</hi> wryteth in his ſixte booke, ſaying:<note place="margin">Macrobiꝰ lib. 6.</note> the beſt &amp; moſte profitable way of reading and hearing, is to immitate thoſe which ſeeme moſte probable, &amp; to conuert the ſayings of other to ſome vſe of thine, whiche thou thinkeſt moſt graue, and moſt to be admyred, which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed maner the pleaſant Latines as alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noble Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians were wont to vſe, which is not onely to heare any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour, to learne his wordes, or to vnderſtande his oration or phraſe of ſpeaking, but of his learning and doctrine, to col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the mellifluous eloquence and right way of liuing, euen as meate receiued onely in the mouth nothing nouriſheth the body except it diſcende into the
<pb facs="tcp:16492:29"/> ſtomacke, and there conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qued and ſodden, in the ende conuerte to fleſhe and bloude, ſo neyther the leſſon that is hearde or read, profiteth any whit the ſtudent, vnleſſe it be conferred to ſome vſe of tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and more wiſdome. The third exerciſe is this, to drawe euery day a lyne by example of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Painter <hi>Appelles,</hi> who would dayly, were he neuer ſo ſore oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyed about other affayres, depaynt or drawe one lyne at the leaſt. And ſo doth the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man put dayly one piece of ſiluer into his treaſury, for many littles make a great, as <hi>Heſiodus</hi> the Poet ſayth:<note place="margin">Heſiodus.</note> 
                     <hi>Paruu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la ſi tentas ſuper adieciſſe puſillis, id<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que frequenter peragas, magnus cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulatur aceruꝰ.</hi> Which is: If thou adde or put little to little, &amp; vſe
<pb facs="tcp:16492:29" rendition="simple:additions"/> it eftſones, therof riſeth a great heape. And in this exerciſe it is not to be laboured howe much we learne dayly, but how wel. Therfore <hi>Appelles</hi> anſwered an vnſkilful Painter who gloried that he had drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an Image ſodenly: I doe not maruell at this, ſayth he, for thou mayeſt drawe many moe ſuch fooliſhe pictures quickly. Wherfore we ought to follow that witty ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Cato, Sat cito ſi ſtat bene.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cato:</note> Inoughe well done is done quickely inough. Wherevpon <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> vſed this adage,<note place="margin">Auguſtus Caeſar.</note> 
                     <hi>Matura lente.</hi> Haſte not to much in thy worke, but do it wiſelye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out muche temerity or raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. For the ſoft circumſpect ſpace profiteth more, than the ſwifte hedlong courſe without all wit and reaſon. The fourth
<pb facs="tcp:16492:30"/> and laſte exerciſe, is to reporte and reuolue at night whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer was learned the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, whiche vſe <hi>Cato</hi> vſed as <hi>Philel.</hi> wryteth in his booke <hi>de e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duca. puero.</hi> And <hi>Apuleius</hi> writeth of a certaine people in <hi>India,</hi> which are called <hi>Gymnoſophiſtae,</hi> which knowe neither to inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit their lande, nor the vſe of tillage, neither to bridle horſes neither to tame bulles, neither to ſhere ſheepe, yet they adored wiſdome greatly. Both aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent mayſters, as alſo yong ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſcholers, haue nothing in more contempt than the ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh ſlouthfulneſſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde. For when as their table was ſpred redy for dinner, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore meate was ſet thereon, all the yong men from diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and offices came to Dine.
<pb facs="tcp:16492:30" rendition="simple:additions"/> Then woulde the mayſter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of eche of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what good he had done that day from the ryſing of the ſunne. Then one would remember howe he had ſet two at vnitie and concord. An other woulde ſay he had o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed his parents commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes: another would ſay he had founde ſomething by practiſe: and an other woulde ſay he had learned ſomewhat. And he which coulde ſhew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, was thruſt dinnerleſſe out of the dores to worke. And ſo ought euery ſtude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at night to practiſe with him ſelfe the propertie of ſheepe, whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is, that when towardes night they be driuen from out the medowes vnto the fieldes, they do eate and chaw againe their meate that they haue ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered
<pb facs="tcp:16492:31"/> of al the day before, and therefore they ſurrender milke into their paſtors. In likewiſe ought the enamored with ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to repeate at nighte both what he hath read, &amp; alſo what he hath hearde, both which be grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded on eloquence, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo which be godly and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in doctrines. And ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he turne into milk, that is that he vſe to ſeeme profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and honeſt of liuing, that others may ſe wherin he hath profited, euen as the ſheepe ſhewe their paſture by their milke, to haue eaten graſſe, &amp; not to haue ſpent the day idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. And alſo it ſhall be verie profitable to examine with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, whether he hath profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more in eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. For wheras he conferreth
<pb facs="tcp:16492:31" rendition="simple:additions"/> with others eyther of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth what he knoweth, &amp; what he doth not know. Whervpon <hi>Sueto</hi> in his boke of the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Grammarians, ſayth:<note place="margin">Sueto.</note> that in the olde time in ſcholes of learning, it was the accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med maner, that the ſcholers ſhoulde in the fore noone con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the one with the other in diſputations, and in the after noone recite thoſe diſputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and arguments by roote.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ What comelineſſe, vertue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie eche man ought to kéepe in all ages.</head>
                  <p>THe lyfe of Vertue or ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie, conſiſteth in two thinges. Firſte, in the comely or nature of it ſelf. And ſecondly, in the decent and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt behauiour toward others,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:32"/> as <hi>Macrobius</hi> teſtifieth, ſaying: that by Vertue a good man is made gouernour and ruler o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer him ſelfe, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ouer the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale. Firſt, it is nedefull that euery man rule him ſelfe before he inſtruct others, whervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Thales Mileſius</hi> a Philoſopher, being demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded who were an vpryghte Prince, he made anſwere: he that ruleth him ſelfe ſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it can not be obiected in his teeth.</p>
                  <p>And how it becommeth eche man to rule and gouerne him ſelfe by Vertue, muſt be conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by diligent labor, which ſhall be declared hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Who ſo wit guide and rule him ſelf honeſtly, muſt kepe ſix precepts.</head>
                  <p>OF which the firſt is, that he learne to holde hys peace, that he loue ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:16492:32" rendition="simple:additions"/> better than iangling talke, for taciturnitie and little talke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tokeneth a wyſe and prudent man. And contrarywiſe, ouer muche pratling betokeneth a foole, who knoweth not to holde his peace, <hi>Macrobiꝰ</hi> ſayth: by ſilence a Pliloſopher doth no leſſe deuine than by ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, that is to ſay, it is no leſſe ſigne of wiſedome to keepe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, than to ſpeake. Whereof <hi>Pythagoras</hi> (as wryteth <hi>Apulei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>) called firſt by te name of a Philoſopher, taught his ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers at the firſte, onely to kepe ſilence. And the firſt inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make a wyſe ſcholer, was to coerce and brydle his tongue, and to repreſſe and kepe backe the wordes within the wall of his teeth. <hi>Socrates</hi> alſo being de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of a certaine man by
<pb facs="tcp:16492:33"/> what meanes euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might attaine vnto wiſdome: he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed him two wayes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſte was, that he keepe cloſe more than he ſpeake, and the other was, that he learne to ſpeake, which was ſingularly ſpoken of him, for it is manifeſtlye knowen by three ſignes, that ſilence ought more to be vſed than loquacitie. Firſt, by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture man hath but one mouth, and two eares, that he ſhoulde not ſpeake all that he heard. The ſeconde ſigne is, by the cuſtome of the auncient Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes, for the Romaynes were wont to depict the Lady <hi>Angerona,</hi> Goddeſſe of ſilence, hauing hir mouth cloſed vppe with wax. And the Egyptians depainted <hi>Harpocrates,</hi> God of ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, ſhutting his mouth with
<pb facs="tcp:16492:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> two fingers. Thirdlye, by the olde aunciente Philoſophers doctrine &amp; learning, who did damnifie nothing in a man more than much iangling, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nature gaue man teeth and lippes before his tongue, for that conſideration, that he might ſuppreſſe and brydle it, leaſt he ſhould become a great chatterer.<note place="margin">Xenocrat.</note> And <hi>Xenocrates</hi> a Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher being inquired of, as touching his ſilence, he made anſwere againe, that he neuer repented for not ſpeaking, but that it ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tymes grieued him that he ſpake. The ſecond pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte is, that he learne to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and ſpeake that that is decent and comelye to ſpeake, not to tell lying tales, but in al things to tell the truth: For he that dare tell that whiche is
<pb facs="tcp:16492:34"/> fayned, &amp; hath not bene ſeene, then is he a lyer and a deceyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full perſon,<note place="margin">Horatius.</note> as <hi>Horace</hi> teſtifieth, neyther oughte any man (as <hi>Plinie</hi> ſayth) ſpeake that which may be hurtfull to the ſpeaker,<note place="margin">Plinius.</note> neyther to vtter backebiting wordes which might diminiſh an other mannes honour, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to goe whiſpering, or as one would ſay, to ſpeake with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his ſleeue, but onely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that which is honeſt, chaſt, profitable and true. And the righte vertuous man doth kepe in ſecret all other, wherv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Ouid</hi> wryteth two trim ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſaying: <hi>Eximia eſt virtus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtare ſilentia rebus. Et contra, grauis eſt culpa tacenda loqui.</hi> Whiche is in our mother tong: Silence is an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vertue, farre paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and exceding all thinges.
<pb facs="tcp:16492:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> And contrarywiſe it is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable offence to vtter thoſe things which ought to be kept in ſecret. Therfore in ſpeaking we ought to kepe this order &amp; lawe, that when we woulde ſpeake, we firſt foreſe, whether it becommeth the place, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time, and alſo the perſons which be there preſent. Secondly, that we ſpeake then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with our ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we might hinder our ſelues or our frien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Thirdly, that he take hede leaſt he doe to muche, that is, that in all things he obſerue a meane and meaſure, and that he committe not to often that which is naught, neither that to little which is good.<note place="margin">Terentius in Andria</note> As <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> ſayth in his Comedy no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated <hi>Andria,</hi> the firſt ſceane. <hi>Nam id arbitror adprime in vita vtile
<pb facs="tcp:16492:35"/> eſſe, vt ne quid nimis.</hi> For I thinke it very neceſſarie to the lyfe of man, in all thinges to kepe a meane. For which cauſe the learned men deſcribe Vertue to ſitte in the midſt. <hi>Eſt modus in rebus. Sunt certi denique fines, quos vltra citraque nequit conſiſtere rectè.</hi> There is a mean in al things, and eche thing hath certaine limitts beyonde whiche, or on this ſyde whiche, Vertue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth not. For Vertue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in a meane, and in all exceſſe and ſuperfluitie, vice taketh vp hir dwelling place. Wherfore, in all things a mean is commendable, and exceſſe alway vituperable.<note place="margin">Heſiodus.</note> Herevpon the Poet <hi>Heſiodus</hi> hath a prety ſaying. <hi>Demidiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> plus toto.</hi> That is to ſaye: A meane is more laudable tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuperfluitie. And
<pb facs="tcp:16492:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> it is a common prouerbe. <hi>Omne nimium vtitur in vitium.</hi> Euery to much is ſtarke naught.<note place="margin">Cleobolꝰ Lindus.</note> And <hi>Cleobolus Lyndus</hi> one of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen wiſe men of Greece, ſaith: The beſt in euery thing, is a meane or meaſure.</p>
                  <p>The fourth precept is, that euery man eſchew and ſlye in him ſelfe, that whiche he ſeeth filthy &amp; vncomely in an other, remembring the Philoſopher <hi>Diogines</hi> his ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, who ſaith.<note place="margin">Diogenes.</note> 
                     <hi>Si vis bonus &amp; virtute praeditus effici, expelle a te quod in alio deſpicis.</hi> If thou deſire to be an honeſt and vertuous man, ſeclude that vice from thy ſelfe, which thou eſpieſt filthy in an other. And <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth, he muſte be a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect vertuous man,<note place="margin">Cicero.</note> that wyll tell his neighbour of his vyce, for we can eaſely and quicklye
<pb facs="tcp:16492:36"/> eſpy other mennes faultes, but our owne we will not knowe. If any deſcend into his owne bowels, and ſearch his owne conſcience, and doe way and conſider with him ſelfe what he is, then will he ceaſe byting his neighbor with his vitious minde, and firſt, he will go and purge him ſelfe from all his vices and ſinfull lyfe, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orne &amp; trimme him ſelfe wyth vertue. Therefore our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt in hys Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, perſuading vs to Vertue, doth commaund vs, firſt to caſt the great beame of ſinne from oute our owne eyes, and after the little mote in oure neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, that we ſhould firſt cure and heale our ſelues, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently other.</p>
                  <p>The fift precept is, to abide
<pb facs="tcp:16492:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> hys eſtate what ſo euer it be, whether it be proſperous or aduerſe, not to ioy ouer much ouer his fortunate lyfe, leaſt ſhe ſodenly turning hir whele, double his ſorrow and penſyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and that he be not too heauy &amp; ſorrowfull for his vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate lyfe, but to learne of <hi>Socrates,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Socrates.</note> in both hys eſtates to kepe one countenance, and one minde.<note place="margin">Plato.</note> Whervpon <hi>Plato</hi> being aſked at a certain time wherby a wiſe man might be knowen, he aunſwered: A wyſe man though he be contemned, will not be moued, neyther ſhal his prayſe or greate name make him arrogant or proude. For Vertue hath none acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with pride, bycauſe it is a vice, neyther doth it admitte the familiaritie of deſperatnes
<pb facs="tcp:16492:37"/> and wrath, bycauſe they be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo vyces. Wherfore it is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prouerbe, <hi>Qui homo in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſis rebus puſilli eſt animi, ille nauti eſt.</hi> Which is thus much to ſay: That man which in aduerſity is fainte hearted, is not to be eſteemed. Therefore a man ought to do both in proſperitie and in aduerſitie, as a certaine Philoſopher did, who in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, would be ſad, &amp; ſaying that after mirth commeth ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and likewyſe in aduerſity he would be mirry, ſaying: that after ſorrowe came mirth, for fortune is euer mutable &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, therfore ought we in proſperitie to looke for aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie enſuing. As <hi>Plaut. in Amph.</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Plaut. in Amphit.</note> 
                     <hi>Ita diis viſum eſt, voluptati vt meror comes ſubſequatur.</hi> For ſo it is the Gods pleaſure, that ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row
<pb facs="tcp:16492:37" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhuld be mirthes waiting mayd. And therfore alſo ought we to thinke thus in aduerſity how that God ſhall ende thys miſery at his will and leyſure, or as <hi>Virgill</hi> ſayth.<note place="margin">Virgilius.</note> It ſhall be ſufficient to haue thought on thoſe euilles, and not alwayes and continually to muſe and thinke thereon.</p>
                  <p>The ſixt and laſte precepte ſhall be, that he indeuour him ſelfe to pleaſe euery honeſt and wyſe man, for thereof deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth great prayſe and vertue: for conſequently it followeth, that who ſo pleaſeth them, is alſo eyther honeſt, or elſe by frequenting their companye learneth honeſty: for good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loue none but good, and the naughty perſon none but euil. Therfore expedient it is, that
<pb facs="tcp:16492:38"/> he who wil obtaine vertue, do applye his induſtrie to pleaſe vertuous men, as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſayth: we muſt chooſe ſome vertuous man whome we muſt alwaye followe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we liue ſo, as though he alwayes ſawe vs, &amp; what ſo euer we doe, to doe it ſo, as though he were preſent at the doing therof: for he may eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye liue an honeſt and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous lyfe, who lyueth after the will and rule of vertuous men, and doeth all his thinges as though they were done before them, euen as women decking and trimming them before a glaſſe, &amp; when they haue ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them ſelues finely and neatly, they wander in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the market, there to be viewed and ſeene.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>¶ Concerning the maners and vertues of all ages.</head>
                  <p>ALthoughe that Vertue and honeſtie do deck and adourne a man, yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, euery age hath his condition of honeſtie, for it is a prouerbe. <hi>Alia vita, alia die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, alios mores poſtulant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For all conditons are not comely for euery age, for ſome become children, ſome youth, ſome yong men, ſome men, and other ſome aged men, for with the age the nature chaungeth, therfore muſt they alſo chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge their maners. For there are v. ages of men, which be theſe: infancie, childehoode, youth, mans age, and olde age, which haue their conditions particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly them ſelues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:39"/>
                  <head>¶ As concerning infancie.</head>
                  <p>INfancie is the firſte age of man after his natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and it is ſo called, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it can not ſpeake, and therfore he can learne no good maners or vertue, bycauſe he is not yet reaſonable, nor hath not the vſe and practiſe of the tongue, neyther hath he any perſeuerance at all. Therefore muſt he onely liue after the wil and pleaſure of the Nurſſe or Mother.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>De Pueritia.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PVeritia</hi> is the ſecond age, when as the infants do begin to ſpeake, hauing not as yet the full vſe of reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It may ſo be, that they be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led children of the Latin word <hi>Bua,</hi> that is a Childes drinke,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:39" rendition="simple:additions"/> which they call <hi>Bua,</hi> vttering their wordes firſt vnperfectly, without wiſedome, reaſon, or vnderſtanding. And theſe the Parents ought to teache, to bring them vp in honeſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and conuerſation. Firſte with theſe maners: that they worſhippe and pray vnto God with a willing heart, that they be obedient to their Parents, that they reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce their elders, that they flye and auoyde all playe and euill company, leaſt they be defiled with vyces be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they attaine vnto reaſon, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte odious thing on earth.<note place="margin">Apuleius.</note> As <hi>Apuleiꝰ</hi> ſayth who woulde not hate and deſdaine that boye whome he ſeeth as though he were a certaine mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, ſtout, bolde and very vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, being as yet vnder age,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:40"/> ſoner to be vnhappy and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitions, than ſtrong of body, being but of tender yeres, and yet of ſtubbern malice and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred? Yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding you can not require perfect wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in a childe, whilſt as yet his childiſhneſſe and imbicili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of witte hath dominion and power ouer him, therefore he playeth with tryfles and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gawes. And for all this, yet muſt you not fauour him ouer muche, leaſt he incline him to vyces, and ſo remaine alway filthy &amp; vncleanly. For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he learneth once in hys youth, that will he vſe for euer. Wherfore they ought diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be inſtructed and nuſſeled vp in theſe precepts.<note place="margin">Phill. li. 8. de educat. liberoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> As <hi>Phille.</hi> wryteth in his eyght booke of the bringing vp of childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that
<pb facs="tcp:16492:40" rendition="simple:additions"/> is, that they worſhip God, that they be gentle, obedient and ſeruiceable in wordes, condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and body: And to vſe a comely cleanly &amp; decent forme of apparell, not to be tale cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, nor lyars, nor beaſtes of fylthy and wicked conditions, not leane of body as Aſſes, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet filthy as Hogs in the myre, neyther ſlouenlyke in their apparell, as beggars or fleſhely and lecherous goates, neyther dul witted like a ſtone or Aſſe. And as ſone as they be once ſeauen yeres olde, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them in cuſtodie to ſchole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, for ſo were the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles wont to do,<note place="margin">Phil. lib. 2. de educat. liberoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> as <hi>Phille.</hi> wryteth in his ſecond booke of the bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vppe of children.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:41"/>
                  <head>De Iuuentute.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IVuentus</hi> is the nexte age to <hi>Pueritia,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Perottus.</note> although that <hi>Perottus</hi> ſayth that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wiſe counſellers do numbers it after <hi>Adoleſcentia,</hi> yet it is before <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcentia</hi> by dayly vſe, which age commeth in, when as the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren can new vtter their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des perfectly and plainly, &amp; are committed to Scholemaſters to be inſtructed, or elſe be redy to be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their charge. And as <hi>Perottus</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Perottus.</note> it is called <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentus,</hi> youth, of this word <hi>Iuua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi> to helpe, bycauſe it waxeth able and potent to helpe hys pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, for it ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſpatch quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his fathers will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, and can put his helpe to many labours, or at leaſt do his will therto. And as
<pb facs="tcp:16492:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>Quintilian</hi> wryteth in his firſte booke and thirde Chapter.<note place="margin">Quintili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus. lib. 1. capit. 3.</note> In this age, parents muſt beware that they do not to much pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per vp their children, to kepe them ſo tender, that no colde winde may blowe ouer them, for that ſoft kinde of bringing vp doth corrupt and debilitate the ſtrength and force, both of the body, and alſo of the witte. And what ſhall this youth do, whiche is thus laſciuiouſlye brought vp? Verely they that be wanto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, petela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiouſly and delicatly kept in this age, will looke for the ſame delicacie all their lyfe after: And when as they can keepe this no longer, eyther for their ſumptuous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, or elſe for lacke of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony, then do they labor by al meanes, by right or by wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
<pb facs="tcp:16492:42"/> to taſt their ſweete lickorouſe and dilicate mouth, then doe they fall into ſuch idleneſſe, play, paſtimes, and thefts, and conſequently into all kinde of wickedneſſe. In this age the children of <hi>Rome</hi> were wont to hang their golden ornaments vp with a roope vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple which they ware aboute their neckes from their infancie, as thoughe they did renounce all childiſheneſſe: And then did they put on a fyne white gown garded with Purple, in token to leaue all childiſh conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and in exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of a better, more pure and honeſt lyfe, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhoulde ſee the whiteneſſe of their gownes, they ſhoulde flye vice, which maketh a man loke blacke, and hated of other, and beholding the brightneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:16492:42" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the purple colour, they ſhuld endeuour them ſelues y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their godly &amp; vertuous lyuing ſhuld ſo ſhine, whereby it might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliat prayſe of all men.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Theſe were the dueties of children.</head>
                  <p>FIrſte to worſhippe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, with hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prayers, and a low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſyncere &amp; an obedient heart, to honour and obey their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, to loue and feare their Maſters, to giue diligent eare to theſe thre: to flye what they forbid, to execute and do what they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund, that thei learne the commaundements of God, heare them taught, ſeeke them out where as they be, &amp; fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to followe them. And it may eaſely be perceyued how
<pb facs="tcp:16492:43"/> that a yong man muſte obey theſe three, for of theſe thre co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth our whole lyfe. Of God we receyue our ſoules, of oure parents our humaine ſubta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and of our maſters the inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſoule, by which our lyfe differs from brute beaſtes. Therefore expedient it is, that we obey them, leaſt we ſeeme vngratefull and thankleſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>De Adoleſcentia.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ADoleſcentia</hi> is the fourth age, whiche beginneth from the fourtenth yeare of our lyfe, and it is called <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcentia</hi> of this worde <hi>Adoleſco,</hi> which ſignifieth to encreaſe, to growe vpwarde, for then man doeth encreaſe in bodye, in ſtrength, in reaſon, in vice, and in Vertue: yet are they more
<pb facs="tcp:16492:43" rendition="simple:additions"/> prone and flexible to vice than to Vertue. And then is euery mans nature and diſpoſition firſt knowen, vnto what he is moſt inclined: for before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> age it can not be knowen through the childiſheneſſe and fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of age. But be they once ſpro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vp this age, they giue their minde to ſome kinde of exerciſe,<note place="margin">Terentiꝰ in Andria</note> as <hi>Terence</hi> in his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie called <hi>Andria</hi> ſaith, either to ryde horſes, or to kepe dogs for hunting, or elſe to worſhip, and learne of ſome notable ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned man. As <hi>Horace</hi> wryteth alſo in his boke intituled <hi>de arte Poetica.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Imberbis Iuuenis tandem cuſtode remoto</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gaudet equis, Canibꝰ, &amp; aprici gramine ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pi.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caercus in vitium flecti, monitoribus asper</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vtilium tardus prouiſor, prodigus aeris,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sublimis, cupiduſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> &amp; amata reli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quere pnix.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:44"/>
                     <l>When as the beardleſſe man,</l>
                     <l>is paſt his Maſters charge:</l>
                     <l>To brydle horſe is his delight,</l>
                     <l>to ſée Dogs runne at large.</l>
                     <l>To hunt the Fox or Hare,</l>
                     <l>to make a merry ſporte:</l>
                     <l>In luſty youth is care,</l>
                     <l>to liue in ſuch a ſorte.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>This age is double, the firſt beginning from .xiiij. to .xviij. and it is called youth bearde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, bycauſe at thoſe yeares yong men be without beards. As <hi>Phoebus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phoebus</note> otherwyſe called <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollo</hi> ſtoode in auncient time in the Temples of the Gentiles without a beard. As <hi>Vale. Max.</hi> wryteth in his firſte booke <hi>de Neglecta religione,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Valerius Maximus lib. 1. de neg. relig.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the ſtory of <hi>Dioniſius Tyrannus Syracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanus.</hi> Then from .xviij. yeares their Bearde doth begynne to grow, and then they be called
<pb facs="tcp:16492:44" rendition="simple:additions"/> yong men with beards, grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to mannes eſtate. And this age doeth precipitate &amp; thruſt downe hedlong a yong man into al kind of vice, in idleneſſe, paſtimes, diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, glotony, luxuriouſneſſe, whore hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting, pride, prodigalitie, and vnto al kinde of ſenſualitie, conſuming &amp; waſting their patrimonie fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolouſlye, nothing weighing their hore haires to come, as al Comedies do plainly declare, which intreate nothing of yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g men, but howe they ſlaſhe out thier goodes on voluptuous pleaſures and delicate ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ How Parents and Maſters ought to traine vp yong men to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and honeſtie.</head>
                  <p>SEing therfore this age is more ready to vyce, than all other ages be,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:45"/> and doeth dayly more &amp; more giue it ſelfe hedlong to youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full luſtes and concupiſcences, euen as a yong Colte whome youth tickeleth, therfore ought yong men of this age to be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned eyther of their parents, or elſe of their Maſters, euen as the wilde ſtarting horſe is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and brydeled of the horſe courſer, with pricking ſpurres. In which thing pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters muſt vſe foure things, if ſo be that they will bring them to any good paſſe, that is to ſay with inſtruction, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> monition, with large promeſſe, &amp; laſte of al, with prayſe &amp; threatnings.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Inſtruction conſiſteth of ſixe Precepts.</head>
                  <p>WHereof the firſt is, as I ſayde before, that they be taught chiefely and
<pb facs="tcp:16492:45" rendition="simple:additions"/> before all things to worſhippe and pray vnto God, who hath giuen eſſence and being to all, hath fed and preſerued al, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no haynous crime vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, no vertuous dede vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, giuing an euerlaſting reward to the good, and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual puniſhment to the euil, and that without his lawfull fauour and grace our mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is able to comprehende no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, &amp; without his eſpeciall grace, we are not able to lyue a moment: And therefore to be carefull, leaſt with our wicked lyfe we offende.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, not to truſte in worldly goodes, and ſpecially in the beauty of the body, for the pulcritude thereof is a very frayle and mutale good,<note place="margin">Virgilius. Eglog. 2.</note> as <hi>Virgil</hi> ſayth in his ſecond <hi>Eglog.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:45"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O formoſe puer nimiùm ne crede colori,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alba liguſtra cadu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vaccinia nigra legu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>O fayre ſweéete boy</l>
                     <l>Do thou not ioy,</l>
                     <l>of thy ſwéet pleaſant face:</l>
                     <l>Truſt not to much</l>
                     <l>That thou art ſuch,</l>
                     <l>beware in any caſe.</l>
                     <l>For Pepper is blacke</l>
                     <l>And hath a good ſmacke,</l>
                     <l>and euery man will it bye:</l>
                     <l>Snowe is white</l>
                     <l>And lyeth in the dyke,</l>
                     <l>and moſt men let it lye.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Neyther let it grieue them, if nature haue not compou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded their limmes as well as ſhee hath done others, but let them labour y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they be farre bewtiful and ſplendent in minde.<note place="margin">Franciſc. Petrar. li. de aduerſ. fortuna.</note> For as <hi>Franciſcus Petrar.</hi> ſayth in hys booke <hi>de aduerſa fortuna. Pulchrius eſt pulchru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fieri.</hi> The faireſt bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is, a man to make him ſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:16492:46" rendition="simple:additions"/> bewtifull, that is: knoweledge and Vertue, which is a farre fairer thing, than to be borne faire and comely of perſonage. And this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement was <hi>Socrates</hi> wont to teach his ſcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, that they ſhould often co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template and behold them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues in a glaſſe: and ſeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues faire of body and face, they ſhould alſo endeuour too make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues faire of mind. For the body co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it a defiled minde, is a gaye and a goodly Sepulchre, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding within it a rotten and a putrified body. Wherfore our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt in hys holy Goſpell, called the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, painted Sepulchres, for that they outwardly appeared religious and honeſt, and were inwardely rauening Wolues.
<pb facs="tcp:16492:47"/> And <hi>Socrates</hi> commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded them alſo, that ſeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues not well ſhaped, they ſhoulde alſo ſeeke the bewty of the minde, with knowledge and vertue, whiche is more noble and of longer continuance than the ſhape of the body.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that they put no co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence nor truſt in their riches and goodes, neyther in their great aboundance of money, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they truſt onely to their ſcience and vertue, hoping in tyme to become riche and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py men, for the wyſe and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned is the true riche man: and worldly ryches are but tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie and quickly loſt. For we reade of many exceeding riche men, who haue in a moment bene moſt infortunate, as was <hi>Croeſus</hi> the moſt riche Prince of
<pb facs="tcp:16492:47" rendition="simple:additions"/> the earth, king of the <hi>Lydians.</hi> Neyther are ryches to be eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as precious Iewels,<note place="margin">Cecero. li. 4. nouae reth.</note> for <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth in his fourth booke <hi>nouae Rethor. Si voles diuitias compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare cum virtute, vix ſatis idoneae eru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, vt ſint virtutis prediſſequae ſiue famu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae.</hi> If thou wilt compare riches with vertue, they are ſcarce fyt for to be hir waiting maids or ſeruants: therefore ought yong men in their flouriſhing witte and ripe age, to prepare a wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring man or guide to leade them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way to olde age, which wayfaring man, is vertue and knowledge. For by them, and through them, the aged man hath honour, prayſe, health, &amp; nouriſhment:<note place="margin">Thales Mileſius.</note> Whervpon <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les Mileſius</hi> a Philoſopher, being demaunded in time paſt what yong men ſhoulde learne, he
<pb facs="tcp:16492:48"/> made anſwere: let them learne thoſe thinges by whiche they may liue in their old age, that is to ſay, vertue &amp; knowledge.</p>
                  <p>The fourth document and precept is, that thei teach them to auoyde that which they ſee hurtfull to another, or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which they ſee contaminate or defile another, &amp; that by other mens damages &amp; miſfortunes they learne wiſedome, and that by them they amende and correct their own wicked life to a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The vyces which corrupt and ruſt men, are diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, lying, tangling talke, vnfayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, diſhoneſtie, carding &amp; dycing, and all ſuch filthie ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, whorehunting, dronken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, prodigalitie, ydleneſſe, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of vicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonnes.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>The fift precept is, that they put before their eies the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple both of good men, and alſo of vicious and wicked me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they may ſee the life and death of them: how the wicked haue bene rewarded wyth puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the good men wyth prayſe. In co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the old auncient Romaynes did veſtite and aray their yong men, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prime of their youth, with gownes decent for men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by little and litle, they might at the laſt creepe to an honeſt lyfe. After that they were ledde to the open Market place, that they might knowe and ſee the life of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be double, the one vitious, the other vertuous, the vitious &amp; peruerſe life to haue an euill ende and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion, but the way to the vertuous lyfe,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:49"/> to be ſtraight and ful of bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and briers, but yet at the laſt to be rewarded with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual beneficial good reward Therfore <hi>Hercules</hi> being at the state of a yong man, chooſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſerue vertue throughe labour and paynes, knowing that after labour their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth a rewarde, than to be in bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage to vyce by idleneſſe.<note place="margin">Cicero. li. 1. Officioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> As <hi>Cicero</hi> wryteth of him in hys firſt booke of Offices.</p>
                  <p>Sixtly, that they be ſtill oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied with labour and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe, and neuer ſuffered to gyue them ſelues to idleneſſe, leaſt they fall into all diſorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red luſts: For as <hi>Ouid</hi> ſayth, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour taketh away all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the fleſh:<note place="margin">Ouidius.</note> 
                     <hi>Otia ſi tollas, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riere Cupidinisarcus.</hi> If thou driue away idleneſſe, loue ſhall haue
<pb facs="tcp:16492:49" rendition="simple:additions"/> no force on thee.</p>
                  <p>Therefore the olde Romay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dyd dayly exercyſe their children in wraſtling, fighting &amp; ſwimming: therefore ought yong men to be exerciſed with dayly labor, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as horſe cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers vſe to breake yong horſes, ryding them dayly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtreate to ſtreate, or in the fieldes, to vſe them to ryding to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpurre and the brydle, who being let ſtyll runne at large, would be paſt mannes might to rule.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of Monition.</head>
                  <p>SEcondly, Parents and Maſters muſt not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſtruct yong men, but warne them alſo of theyr faults. If they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit any crime, they ought to be taught to doe better and more vertuouſlye.
<pb facs="tcp:16492:50"/> And ofte tymes to commen in the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of them of honeſtie, and honeſt men, that at the length by dayly admonition &amp; warning, they may become y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more honeſt, for wordes doe moue the minde, &amp; that which a man heareth ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and incloſed in his hearte. And that they exhorted &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed to imitate the foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteppes of their Godly and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerende Parents, of their ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Kinſfolks &amp; Neuewes, as <hi>Aeneas</hi> in the .xij. boke of <hi>Aeneidos</hi> doth perſwade and admoniſh his ſonne <hi>Aſcanius,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of him his father he ſhould learne vertue: ſaying.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diſce puer virtutem ex me, verum<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> laborem,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fortunam ex alijs, nùnc te mea dextera bello.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Defenſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dabit, &amp; magna inter praemia ducet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tu facito, mox cum matura adoleucrit aetas,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sis memor.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>O Childe learne vertue here of me,</l>
                     <l>the roote of labour true:</l>
                     <l>Which ſhall thée leade to dignitie,</l>
                     <l>that neuer thou ſhalt rue.</l>
                     <l>But ſcape to ſhore, and ſwim to lande</l>
                     <l>when other ryches fleete:</l>
                     <l>A perfect guide by thée to ſtande,</l>
                     <l>a Lanterne to thy féete.</l>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of large and liberall promiſe.</head>
                  <p>THirdely, that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe them to get great rewardes of euery man in euery place, and alwayes if in caſe they ſeke after Vertue, as <hi>Horace</hi> ſayth in his Epiſtles.<note place="margin">Horatius. in epiſtolis.</note> 
                     <hi>I bone, quo virtus tua te ducit, I pede fauſto, Grandia laturus meritoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia.</hi> Go happely vertuous man whether ſo euer thy Vertue ſhal conduct and leade thee, in hope to bring home great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:16492:51"/> for thy deſerts. Go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes O ye yong men, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertue ſhall leade you, for great is your rewarde, for he hath al things plentiouſly, and to him that ſeketh vertue there wanteth nothing.<note place="margin">Plautus.</note> As <hi>Plaut.</hi> teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifieth <hi>in Amph. Comaedi.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of prayſe and threatnings.</head>
                  <p>FOurthly and laſt of all, aſcribe prayſe to yong men, if they continue &amp; proſper in vertue. For prayſe is a great helpe, and ayde to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and ende their courſe that they haue determined.<note place="margin">Ouid. lib. 5 de triſtibus</note> As <hi>Ouid</hi> ſheweth in the fifth booke, <hi>de triſtibus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Deni<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> nòn paruas animo dat gloria vires,</l>
                     <l>Et foecunda facit pectora laudis amor.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Finally, glory doth encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and ſtrengthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the minde,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:51" rendition="simple:additions"/> and the loue &amp; deſyre of fame doth make men fruitfull. For al men as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, are tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and inflamed with the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t deſire and hote loue of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and prayſe.<note place="margin">Quintilan</note> 
                     <hi>Quint.</hi> alſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth the prayſe of yong me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they profit in vertue: And alſo he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth threatnings for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if that they be ſluggiſh and vnwilling to attaine vnto vertue and honeſtie, and not threatnings onely, but grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous and ſmarting ſtrypes:<note place="margin">Cicero lib. 4. nouae rethoricae.</note> As <hi>Cicero</hi> teſtifieth in his .iiij. boke <hi>nouae Rhetor.</hi> ſaying: <hi>Qui Adoleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centum peccatis ignoſcendum putant oportere, falluntur: propteria quod ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas illa no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt impedimento bonis ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diis. Apti ſunt ad bona diſcenda, non minus qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mala. At hii ſapienter fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt, qui Adoleſcentes maxime caſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant, vt quibus virtutibus omnem vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16492:52"/> poſsint tueri, eas in aetate maturiſsima ſibi comparent.</hi> They that thinke it good to remitte yong men their faultes, are deceyued: for ſo much that age is a furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance to good &amp; vertuous ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: for they are apt &amp; prompt no leſſe to learn goodneſſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vyce. But they are moſt wyſe, who do chaſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yong men, that in their rypeſt age they may gette ſuche vertues, by which they may defende all their life after.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of the offices and duetie of yong men.</head>
                  <p>YOng men haue dyuers offices. Firſt they muſt chooſe, prepoſe and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the trade of their ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing which they will vſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their life: as we read that
<pb facs="tcp:16492:52" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>Hercules</hi> did. And as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maynes were accuſtomed to bring their yong men into the common Market place, appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relled with gownes as men, and there ſhould they flyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brode nuttes, with which they had played a greate whyle. They ſhould reiect their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ages youthfulneſſe, and ſhould endeuour to liue an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt mans life. For he that wil liue amongſt men, muſt not excede the honeſt meane of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing.</p>
                  <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Cicero, lib. 1. offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciorum.</note> as <hi>Cicero</hi> teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in his firſt boke of Offices. A yong man ought to reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce his elders, and by the good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly admonitions and ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere honeſty of the beſt &amp; moſt godly of them, to inſtitute and prepoſe his kinde of liuing, to
<pb facs="tcp:16492:53"/> brydle him ſelfe from luſtes, &amp; from all fooliſh appetites, and that he exerciſe with labour, &amp; with pacience and ſufferance, both of the body &amp; of the mind, that he may be apte and fitte both for the warres &amp; for Ciuil affayres. And when as he is diſpoſed to recreate and quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken his ſprites and giue him ſelfe to ſome paſtime, that he beware of intemperance, but alway vſe reuerence &amp; ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe, not to be too prodigal and laſciuious, but reuerent, and ſpecially in thoſe thinges at which he would haue his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and ſeniors preſent. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, that both in place &amp; in tyme they thinke them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues men, and not beaſtes, and for that cauſe their maners to exceede the maners and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb facs="tcp:16492:53" rendition="simple:additions"/> of beaſtes, and that they thinke them ſelues yong men, and not children or babes, to play as children: neyther that they thinke them ſelues men or fathers, that of them ſelues they ſhould be wyſe inoughe, but that they lacke as yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions and godly leſſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of mans age.</head>
                  <p>THe fifth age is called mannes age, when as a man is growen to his full rype age, and that his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is paſt growth, &amp; his beard buddeth from out his chinne. And this age is moſt apt and fitte to receyue vertue and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie. For it is of force both by reaſon and of the body to embrace vertue. For of the Latin word (whiche is attrybuted to thys
<pb facs="tcp:16492:54"/> age) that is to ſay <hi>Vir,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Vertue is deryued: for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſillable, <hi>tus,</hi> to this word <hi>Vir,</hi> it is made <hi>Virtus.</hi> For Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue was firſte nominated of this Latin worde <hi>Vir</hi> for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, bicauſe that man onely is able to receyue and learne vertue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of the honeſt life of man.</head>
                  <p>MAnnes lyfe ought to be altogether honeſt and vertuous. For he ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not a perfect honeſt life, who vſeth not all Vertues, though he offende but in ſome. Therefore a man ought to be prudent, iuſt, chaſt, and ſtrong. He muſt be prudent, that he may do eche thing prudently, wiſely, and warely, he muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber both what he hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and what he hath done, to
<pb facs="tcp:16492:54" rendition="simple:additions"/> order thoſe thinges that he hath preſently to do ryghtly, to forcaſt and prouide for time to come, whatſoeuer he doth, to do it wyſely, and alway to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the ende: for it is a filthie thing, as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">Cicero</note> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende to ſay had I wiſt. And <hi>Terence</hi> alſo in <hi>Adelphos</hi> ſayth:<note place="margin">Terentiꝰ in Adelp.</note> 
                     <hi>Iſtud eſt ſapere, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quod ante oculos eſt ſolum videre, ſed que futura ſunt proſpicere.</hi> It is a wyſe thing not onely to vſe the time preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, but to forſe the things to come. He muſt be alſo iuſt, hurting or da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nifying none, but frendly to all men, to ſet vnity and concord betwene all men. Moreouer he muſt be godly &amp; gentle in al his words and dedes, faythfull, truſty and conſtant. For fayth, as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth, is the foundation of iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice: he muſt be alſo temperate
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:55"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:56"/> in al things, vſing a meane be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two extremities: mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, chaſt, moderate, ſparing, ſober and ſhamefaſt.</p>
                  <p>He muſt be ſtrong withall, not in the force of the body, but in the operation of the minde: not fearefull and weake min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the tyme of trouble, not to be daſht out of countenance with euery miſhap or euill for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, but boldely to go againſt it. Let him not be ſodenly mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued &amp; feared, but be of a ſtrong courage howe ſoeuer the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter chaunce or happen. Yet let him brydle hys gredy deſire and wrathful anger aboue all thinges, neyther deſire foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhe gawdes as children, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let him moued with anger do any thing. Therefore <hi>Plato,</hi> being aſked what maner of
<pb facs="tcp:16492:56" rendition="simple:additions"/> men was ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt: he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he which can refraine his owne anger.</p>
                  <p>Finally, a vertuous man oughte to obſerue theſe two precepts. Firſt, that he be ſuch a one as he woulde haue him ſelfe counted to be. As <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth in his ſecond boke of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, that <hi>Socrates</hi> ſayd,<note place="margin">Cicero. li. 2. offi.</note> the way vnto glory is ſhort &amp; eaſy to be adopted, if euery man ſtudy to be as he would he ſhoulde be eſteemed. The ſecond precept is, that he take héede leaſt he loſe the name of an honeſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by this precept of <hi>Ouid.</hi>
                     <q>
                        <l>Omnia ſi perdas, famam ſeruare memento,<note place="margin">Ouidius.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Qua ſemel amiſsa, poſtea nullus eris.</l>
                     </q> Which is in Engliſh. If thou leeſe all thinges, remember to kepe thy name &amp; honeſt fame, which, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt loſt, thou
<pb facs="tcp:16492:57"/> ſhalt be regarded as no body. And that euery man may kepe it, let him learne and followe this precept of <hi>Horace,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horatius.</note> written in his Epiſtles.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Inter cuncta leges &amp; percontabere doctos,</l>
                     <l>Qua ratione queas traducere lenitèr aeuum.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Amongſt all thinges, reade &amp; demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the learned clarkes, howe and by what meanes thou mayſt lead thy life peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of olde age.</head>
                  <p>THe ſixt laſt age, is olde age, to the which age, wiſdome and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie are propriate, which old men haue gotten and adopted, either by the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g courſe of their lyfe, either by knowledge or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience. Wherfore their office and duetie is, as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:57" rendition="simple:additions"/> in his firſt booke of Offices,<note place="margin">Cicero li. 1. offi.</note> to adiuuate and helpe yong men, their frendes, and the publike weale, with good councell and wiſedome. In conſideration whereof, <hi>Romulus</hi> the firſt buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> elected and choſe an hundreth aged perſons, as <hi>Lyuius</hi> writeth, who for their counſell &amp; wiſedome, ſhould haue the gouernement of the Citie. And therefore of this worde, <hi>Senibus,</hi> for aged me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Senat was called, <hi>Senatus,</hi> which is as muche to ſay, as a collection or companie of olde aged me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the old men ſhould he Rectors and Guydes of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp; an example of honeſtie to yong men. In which reſpect honour &amp; dignitie is attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and giuen vnto them as to the Image &amp; portiture of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:58"/> the doctors and teachers of honeſtie and vertue. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, it is the office &amp; dutie of olde men, to flye auarice and couetouſneſſe, which raigneth in them plentifully: and alſo that they eſchew al ſlouth and laſciuiouſneſſe, weighing with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grey haires in their heade and the croked body poſtulateth &amp; requireth. Truly that they vſe graue and vertuous maners and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and remember that they do dayly draw nearer &amp; nearer death, and that their graue is at hand. Their body is bowed downe towardes the ground, whereby they may know, that by death they ſhall immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enter into earth. Wherefore they ought to ſet a ſyde all the pleaſures and delightes of the
<pb facs="tcp:16492:58" rendition="simple:additions"/> worlde, and giue them ſelues wholy to loke for death, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byde his comming. Wherefore it were good that they knewe this verficle of <hi>Horace.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Luſisti ſatìs, edisti ſatìs, at<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> bibisti,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Horatius,</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tempus abire tibi eſt, ne potum largius aequo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rideat, &amp; pulſet laſciua decentius aetas.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quae erga alios, deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et hoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es deceat honeſtas.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>Now youthfull age hath run his race,</l>
                     <l>an hoarie heade we ſée:</l>
                     <l>From trifling toyes &amp; <hi>Bacchus</hi> fare</l>
                     <l>auerted looke thou bée.</l>
                     <l>For earth doth chalenge all hir right,</l>
                     <l>and death doth watch hir pray:</l>
                     <l>With ſtealing ſteps, euen as by night</l>
                     <l>the théefe doth vs aſſay.</l>
                     <l>Whilſt time permits for mercy craue</l>
                     <l>in vertue tende thy race:</l>
                     <l>Do good for yll, ſo ſhalt thou haue,</l>
                     <l>in heauen a dwelling place.</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hodiè mihi, cràs tibi.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cito pede labitur aetas.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:59"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dum vires anni<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan>, ſinunt, tollerate laborem,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iam venict tacito curua ſenecta pede.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ The thirde Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T auaileth but a little to haue the knowledge of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and honeſtie, vnleſſe it be practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and had in vre.<note place="margin">Cicero.</note> For <hi>Cicero in Offic.</hi> ſayth: <hi>Quod omnis laus virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, non in cognitione, ſed in actione, conſiſtet.</hi> The prayſe of vertue conſiſteth not in knoweledge thereof, but in the vſing &amp; fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction therof. And in his boke <hi>de Amicitia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. de Amicitia.</note> he ſayeth: <hi>Tum virtutis praemium &amp; fructus maxime capitur, quum in proximum quenque confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> The greateſt fruit &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite of vertue, is when it is em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to the commoditie of all thy neyghbours. The vſe of
<pb facs="tcp:16492:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> Vertue muſt be referred, both towards God, &amp; alſo towards man, for we were borne in the obedience, both of God &amp; man: Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, we owe one duety towards God, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to man.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ What our duety is to God wardes.</head>
                  <p>HOneſtie to God wardes, conſiſteth in the adoring and worſhipping of god.<note place="margin">Lactantiꝰ lib. 3.</note> As <hi>Lactant.</hi> wryteth in his third boke: <hi>Seruiendum eſt religioni.</hi> We muſt doe reuerence to religion, the which, who ſo doeth not imitate, proſtrateth him ſelfe towards the ground, he folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the lyfe of beaſtes, and vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ſecludeth all humanitie, &amp; curteſie: for in the knoweled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging and worſhipping of God,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:60"/> all wiſedome and ſapience co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth onely.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore, if any man wyll queſtion with him who ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth perfect wiſdome, for what cauſe he was borne into thys worlde: he will anſwere him by and by, that he was borne to worſhip, honour, and obey the omnipotent and eternall God, who created vs for that cauſe, that we ſhould ſerue him as our Lorde and creator.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶Of our duety towards men.</head>
                  <p>IMmediately and nexte after God, we owe a due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and a reuerence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards men:<note place="margin">Lactantiꝰ</note> For as <hi>Lactantius</hi> writeth in his booke: It is the firſt office and duetie of iuſtice to be ioyned with God, ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with man. And Chriſt in his
<pb facs="tcp:16492:60" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſacred goſpell ſayth: Loue thy Lorde God, and thy neighbor as thy ſelfe. Man ought to be as a God to men, in mercy, in lenitie, &amp; pietie, aiding the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigated &amp; laborious, helping the poore and nedy with foode and lyuing, defending the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therleſſe and poore widdowes cauſe. Secondly, what we owe to euery man, I ſhall declare hereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of our duety towardes our Countrey.</head>
                  <p>THe firſt and hyeſt place among men, our natiue Countrey poſſeſſeth: to whome the olde auncient Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers (as <hi>Phille.</hi> wryteth in his fourth booke <hi>de educat libero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum</hi>) gaue the preeminence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue parents,<note place="margin">Phil. li. 4. de educat. liberoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> in conſideration
<pb facs="tcp:16492:61"/> that we were more bound to our contrey tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to our pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: for which cauſe,<note place="margin">Plato.</note> 
                     <hi>Plato</hi> ſaid: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our Countrey claimeth part of our birth, for we were born to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite oure Countrey: for wee may profite our countrey fiue wayes, or with fiue kinde of people: firſt, with labour, for the honour and prayſe of our Countrey, to ſtudy and ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour vs to be ſuch, and ſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, as in time to come, we may be an honour to our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and that it, by the meanes of vs, may aggregate &amp; heape vp glory to it ſelfe for euer.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, if ſhe be fooliſh and vnlearned, to inſtruct hir with prudencie and counſell. For it is our duetie to teach the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. Thirdly that we prouide and prepare our commoditie
<pb facs="tcp:16492:61" rendition="simple:additions"/> and profite, that euen in the ſame we may be thankfull to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land which hath borne, nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed &amp; brought vs vp. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that we defende hir eyther with prudence, or with ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth and force, howſoeuer the time &amp; neceſſitie ſhall require. Fifth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if nede require, and that ſhe can not otherwiſe be redemed ans deliuered, that we prepare our ſelues, euen to dy in hir de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and quarrel, which death is eſteemed and reputed moſt honeſt. Herevpon <hi>Horace</hi> ſayd:<note place="margin">Horat.</note> 
                     <hi>Dulce, &amp; decorum eſt, pro patria mori.</hi> which thing many men haue ventured, as you may reade more plainly in <hi>Liuius</hi> workes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Our duety towards our parents.</head>
                  <p>NExt after God and our Countrey, we ought to reuerence and obey our
<pb facs="tcp:16492:62"/> parents, as we are commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, both by the ſacred &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane ſcriptures, and them we muſt alſo worſhip, both wyth vertue and honeſtie. We ought to ſhew fiue poynts of honeſtie towards our parents. Firſt, in fulfilling their will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in honeſt things. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in ſeruing them to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt of our power. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in honouring them, both in wordes and dedes, not to mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or murmure againſt them. In deede and ieſture, to reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence them, bare headed &amp; ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded knees. Fourthly, in ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vs, that is to ſay, by our profite in vertue &amp; knowledge, that they may at ſome times get prayſe and honour of vs in the preſence of other, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate from them in honeſt
<pb facs="tcp:16492:62" rendition="simple:additions"/> condicion &amp; vertuous lyuing. Fifthly, in nouriſhing them, if that they be ouerlade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie or age, whiche thinges beaſtes doe vſe, and eſpecially the Curlewes who feede their parents in their olde age.<note place="margin">Cicero, de Orat.</note> And <hi>Cicero</hi> in his booke <hi>de, Orat.</hi> hath this ſaying: <hi>Pietas, nihil aliud eſt, quàm humanitas erga pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes,</hi> Piety, is nothing elſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gentleneſſe to our parents.<note place="margin">Franciſcꝰ Phile. de educat. liberoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                     <hi>Franciſcus Philel. de educat. liberoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> wryteth in his thirde Chapter of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame boke concerning the dutie of chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to their parents, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they bee not able during their life, to render ſufficient grateful tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks, yet they ought to do to the vttermoſt of their power, what they may, vſing them moſt gently, moſt curte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, attending on them dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:63"/> fauoring their benigne perſwaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, obeying their eaſy commaundements, to proue &amp; allow their willes, pleaſures &amp; deliberations, eyther to goe or to tarry, eyther to ſpouſe at their determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as though they were diuine and celeſtiall wordes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements, not to rebell or mutter when as they ſhal be ſtirred with the inſtigation of coller, paciently to abide their mines &amp; threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. But when as they ſhall bid or commaund that which is vnhoneſt or vnlawful to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, but gentlely &amp; reuerently without curſing or euill ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ What chaunce hath befallen them, which haue not giuen eare to their parents teachings.</head>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:63" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THey which haue beene wicked and froward to their parents, haue ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer proſpered, as olde wryters do recorde. <hi>Oreſtes</hi> a Gretian, bycauſe he ſlewe his mother <hi>Clytemneſtra,</hi> was tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one of the furyes of hell. And <hi>Naero</hi> a Romain Prince, bicauſe he was a parricide ouer his mother, was euer after cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for the moſt tyraunt on earth. In the auncient time within the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> the parents ſlayers were yerked and puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with a moſt vile death, for they were included within a ſack of leather, with the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of dogs, ſerpents, and cockes, and ſo dimitted headlong into the deapth of the Sea.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:64"/>
                  <head>¶ Of the duetie towardes our Scholemaſters.</head>
                  <p>COnſequently after our pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, we owe reuerence to ſcholemaſters and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructors, for they are other pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents: for which conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles would haue ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters in the place &amp; rowme of parents.<note place="margin">Iuuenal.</note> As <hi>Iuuenall</hi> writeth in his Satires. For Schole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters are parents of minds, for they giue the lyfe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mind, that is to ſay, knowledge and vertue, where as parents giue but onely the life of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body. In reſpect whereof, ſcholemaſters are to be regarded nexte after parents, and are worthy of no leſſe reuerence.<note place="margin">Phille. li. 4 Cap. 7.</note> For as <hi>Phill.</hi> wryteth in his fourth booke &amp; ſeauenth Chapter, it is dayly
<pb facs="tcp:16492:64" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſeene how they flouriſh in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which haue obeyed their Scholemaſters documentes. Amongſt whom <hi>Traianus</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour triumphed, &amp; <hi>Caeſar</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and prayſed of al men in his time for his excellent &amp; ſinguler vertue. And this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuerenced &amp; adored his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Plutarch,</hi> moſt willingly and worthily. <hi>M. Antonius</hi> a Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine, the holyeſt &amp; moſt ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Prince, did erect golden Images in his houſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of his Scholemaſters. <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero</hi> alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prince of eloquence, for that he was eſteemed the fyneſt Latiniſt in earth, he ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated his maſters ſeuerally, and by name in his egregious workes. And as many as haue at any tyme exceeded in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and honeſtie, haue wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped
<pb facs="tcp:16492:65"/> feruently, loued &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyly magnified and extolled their inſtructor by whom they receyued thoſe former vertues.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of thoſe who haue diſhonoured and defamed their inſtructors and Maſters.</head>
                  <p>SVch as haue contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; vituperated their teachers, haue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end proued moſt dulheaded dolts, and moſt vile and filthy in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. As amongſt which, <hi>Nae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> that cruel tyrant was chiefe, whom all wryters condemne and accuſe giltie of ouer much wickedneſſe: for he ſlewe hys Scholmaſter <hi>Seneca</hi> moſt cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and moſt villanouſly. For in remunerating his ſtripes that he had ſuffered of his mayſter in his youth, inſtigated incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently
<pb facs="tcp:16492:65" rendition="simple:additions"/> with the furious rage of coller, &amp; for the curriſh mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice he bare vnto vertue, &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous men, ſent vnto hym by a Centurion to electe &amp; chooſe his death, with diobolicall fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie when as he perceyued, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to be ſette in a veſſell of hote water, and to haue hys vaynes opened, and ſo to dye, which malecious crime and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of his maſter, declared the blunt fyled witte of <hi>Nuro.</hi> Futhermore, <hi>Beroal. in orat, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerb,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Beroaldus in orat. prouerb.</note> ſayth, that who ſo ſeeketh fame by the malidictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byting of his Maſter, ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſlaunderous him ſelfe, &amp; ſhall be expulſed the company of honeſt men as a reprobate, he ſhalll be feared as a Viper, and he ſhal be a common hate, as though he had ſlaundered
<pb facs="tcp:16492:66"/> his parents, for the Maſter is the parent and the ſhape of the mind, whom vnleſſe we honor in euery place and among all men, we haue condignely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to be called flagitious and malepert.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Offices towardes our Maſters.</head>
                  <p>WHerefore, we ought to ſhew foure kinde of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties towards our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters. Firſt, to loue them as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely as our parents. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in all honeſtie to obey their commaundementes. Thirdly, to be gratefull and thankefull vnto them, during this life.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, that we labour with vigila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſtudie to become as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert in knoweledge as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, or rather more. This is
<pb facs="tcp:16492:66" rendition="simple:additions"/> a lawfull and and a decent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention for ſcholers to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tend, either to be equal with his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in knowledge and ſcience, eyther elſe to exceede him. And ſo, many haue growen more perite and ſkilfull than their Maſters: As <hi>Beroaldus</hi> gloryed that he had had many Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, &amp; in the ende reade lector to them all.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Towards our Kinſfolkes and Affinitie.</head>
                  <p>WHat our dewtie is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes our Kinſfolkes &amp; Affinitie, which are ioyned vnto vs in bloude, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by father or mother ſyde, our owne reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal perſwade vs ſufficiently, that we be vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as vnto our ſelues, to loue them as our ſelues, for they
<pb facs="tcp:16492:67"/> are nothing elſe but euen as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we. They are parts &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of our bloude, of our ſtock, and of our progenie, wherfore we take them for none other, than the proper me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of our owne body, that whatſoeuer we would not haue done vnto vs, that ſame we ſhould depell from them, no leſſe to profite them, than our ſelues, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe we ſhoulde be worthely called ingrate. Euen as he is iuſtly termed a foole which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth one parte of his body more than an other, ſo he ſhall merrite the name of a tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kleſſe perſon, which wil not be ready to helpe his coſin of his owne bloude, both with ayde, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo with counſell, for the lawe of nature biddeth vs ſo to doe.</p>
                  <p>And in the Goſpell of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour
<pb facs="tcp:16492:67" rendition="simple:additions"/> Ieſus Chriſt, we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to loue our neighbors as our ſelfe. And they are but right neighbours, who be of our affinitie and kinred.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Towards Frends.</head>
                  <p>FIfthly, we ought to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence our Frendes, which reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we are taught ſufficiently of the moſt famous Clearks, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>Cicero,</hi> in his booke, <hi>de amici.</hi> For there are ſixe duties to be done to our Frendes. Firſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund of our frends nothing which is indecore or diſhoneſt, neither to do ought for thy fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des pleaſure, but that which ſhall be decent &amp; lawfull. The ſecond, is to reioyce no leſſe at thy frendes proſperitie than at thine owne. In aduerſitie to
<pb facs="tcp:16492:68"/> lament his caſe and fortune, and to reuiue, conſolate, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort him agine, eyther with counſell or otherwiſe, to the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſte of thy power, not to forſake them, playing the part as Swallowes,<note place="margin">Cicero. li. 4 Reth.</note> who (as <hi>Cicero</hi> wryteth in his fourth booke of Rhetoricke) will be with you during the Sommer, but as ſone as they perceyue Winter comming, they flye altogether away into the hotter cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tries. The thirde law, is to will and nill the ſelfe ſame thing wyth our frendes, our ſtudies and delectations to be all one with theirs. For contrary ſtudies &amp; dyuers conditions, interrupt and burſt the boundes and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittes of frendſhip: As <hi>Cicero</hi> writeth in the ſame boke.<note place="margin">Cicero.</note> The fourth, is to doe nothing more
<pb facs="tcp:16492:68" rendition="simple:additions"/> to our frends than we would be done vnto. For <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth:<note place="margin">Cicero.</note> 
                     <hi>Amicus eſt quaſi alter idem.</hi> Thy frende is as an other thou, &amp; be one heart in two bodies, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ought to loue them, as our ſelues, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we labor with loue to ouercome the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and not to be ouercommend of them, which is the moſt filthie thing on earth. Fifthly, frendſhippe is to be weighed, (as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth) not for the hope of gaine or lucre, as the common ſort vſe nowe a dayes, that ceaſſing the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, they will alſo forget fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritie: but frendſhip is to be loked in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only loue of the hart, and then it ſhall continue lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt: and then we ſhal be more redier to giue our frend a gift, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to receyue one of him. The ſixt and laſt is, often tymes to
<pb facs="tcp:16492:69"/> obey our frends. For as <hi>Terence</hi> ſayth:<note place="margin">Terentius</note> 
                     <hi>Obſequum amicos parat.</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce getteth frends. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, not to caſt in his teeth to whom thou haſt giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy gift. For as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth, it is an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious kinde of people vpbray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their duties, which ought to haue remembred to whom he did them, and not who did them.<note place="margin">Cicero. li. 2. vet. reth.</note> And in his ſecond booke <hi>veteris Rethor.</hi> he ſaith: <hi>Imprudens eſt ille qui pro beneficio non gratiam ſed mercedem poſtulat.</hi> He is a foole, who for his benefite loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes not for thankes, but for a rewarde. But in caſe we ſhall at any tyme receyue a profyte at our frends hand, we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by the ſame <hi>Cicero</hi> to imitate the fertile fields, who ſurrender more vnto the ſower than they receyued. In like
<pb facs="tcp:16492:69" rendition="simple:additions"/> maner ought we in frenſhip, if we be able, to render more than we receyued, eyther elſe to ſay we are not of abilitie to recompence them wyth lyke meaſure, yet if fortune laughe at any tyme more amiably, I hope to be grate and thankfull.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Towards Felowes.</head>
                  <p>THat familiaritie of men which we do nuncupate ſocietie, is in all pointes like amitie. For ſocietie is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe than a frendly fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaritie, coniunct and ioyned within them ſelues. And in chooſing thy companions and felowes, thou muſt firſt labour to chooſe them that be honeſt and of a good name, by whom thou mayeſt learne to amende
<pb facs="tcp:16492:70"/> thy faultes. And when as we haue gotten ſuch honeſt and alowable Mates, we muſt ſo behaue our ſelues toward the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as we may kepe theſe ſixe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts. Firſt, that we be to them as to our frendes. Secondly, that we obſerue theſe .v. things of whiche <hi>Terence</hi> ſpeaketh in his Comedy of <hi>Andria,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Terentius in Andr.</note> that is, that we learne and frame our ſelues to abide and ſuffer the maners, rytes, ieaſtures of our fellowes, not to be moued to anger at euery worde ſpoken, but to beare all things pacient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; with a merry countenance, and alſo that we apply our ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues wholy to the honeſt becke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings &amp; ſignes of our fellowes. Thirdly, to practiſe their medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, to do as they doe, if at the leaſt it be honeſt, wherfore,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:70" rendition="simple:additions"/> it is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prouerbe: <hi>Viuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum eſt moribus praeſentium, vel ſiue (quod aiunt) capitis no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe moroſum.</hi> We muſt liue after the faſhio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of others, and not after the fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of our owne heade. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we be aduerſary to none, but to flye &amp; auoyde ſtryfe, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, and brawlings. In no caſe to ſowe diſcorde. Fifthly, that we preferre our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore none, and that we eſteme not our ſelues better than the reſt, but equall. Wherevpon it is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſaying, among fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes there ought to be no or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der but one equal with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, and no extolling of one aboue the other. And to theſe little Precepts we may well adde two more, of which the firſt is, not to byte nor ſlaunder thy fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes behind their backe. The
<pb facs="tcp:16492:71"/> ſecond is, to reproue thy felow, if he offende (but that gently &amp; in a ſecrete place) not before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt, for that is to contempne and deſpiſe thy fellow, and not frendly to tel his fault: for fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des reproue the faultie ſecrete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and flatterers ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nly before the multitude.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Towardes aged men.</head>
                  <p>THe old grey headed ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom olde age hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted, ought alſo to be reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced, for he deſerueth ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for his long lyfe, in which (what with experience, vſe and knoweledge) he hath learned much prudencie. In conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration whereof, he ought to be honoured as the manſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> houſe of knowledge, as in whom all wiſedome is lodged. And there be three thinges wherewith
<pb facs="tcp:16492:71"/> aged me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are to be reuerenced. Firſt,<note place="margin">Cicero.</note> as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth in his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, that their labors may be diminiſhed for lack of ſtrength of the body, which by age is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repted. Secondly, they are to be reuerenced with ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle, chaſt and modeſt wordes, to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate by the frendly name of Father or Mother, not to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe them with opprobryes, as nequitie us knaues, but to ſay or do nothing before them, but that which ſhall be both ciuill and allowable. Wherev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Ouid</hi> in his fifth <hi>de Faſt.</hi> hath theſe pretie verſes.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Magna fuit quondam capitis veuerentia tam</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ſuo praecio ruga ſenilis erat.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Verba quis auderet coram ſene digna rubore</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dicere? cenſur am longa ſenecta dabit.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>Haue ſome regarde &amp; beare in minde,</l>
                     <l>thine elders to ſalute.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:72"/>
                     <l>Acknowledge them as thou doſt ſtud,</l>
                     <l>thy betters conſtitute.</l>
                     <l>As ſage and graue, in honeſtie</l>
                     <l>the perfect Lanterne light:</l>
                     <l>Which thou oughteſt of a certaintie</l>
                     <l>to follow with thy might.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Thirdly, we muſt follow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both in deedes and ieaſtures, that deſcende from honeſtie, to reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce them hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king curteſie modeſtly, which thing the old auncient Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes did dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly kepe and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, ordeyning this law, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny paſſed by an aged man, not vncouering his head, he ſhould ſuffer the puniſhement of the heade.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Towards Women.</head>
                  <p>WE owe alſo a reuerence to honeſt &amp; vertuous wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for two cauſes.
<pb facs="tcp:16492:72"/> Firſt, bycauſe they are our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and our Nurſſes, &amp; take more payne in bringing vppe children, than the father doth. Secondly, bicauſe that wyth ſhamefaſtneſſe they worſhippe vertue, which vertue is much eſteemed, as we reade of many Matrones amongſt the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riographers. Therefore they ought to be reuerenced with a triple kinde of honeſtie. Firſt, to temper thy tongue, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as thou commeſt among them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laſciuious &amp; wanton talke. For when as they be ſhamefaſt, there ought nothing to be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before them, but what ſhal be honeſt and decent. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to refrayne from vncomely ieaſture or behauiour, which make the man vicious. All things muſt be done modeſtly,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:73"/> for it becommeth vs to vſe ſuch ieaſture and maners as the companie is. Therefore when as women are taken for wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of ſhamefaſtneſſe, it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth vs alſo to be ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt and chaſt whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as we hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen among them. Thirdly, to auoyde all brawling, &amp; figh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting amongſt them, for they be weake &amp; vnable to reſiſt them which do them wrong, and it ſhall be but ſmall prayſe to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome a woman, eyther elſe to ſtrike hir as the ſaying is.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Towarde ſtraungers and peregrines.</head>
                  <p>THere be alſo foure offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces or dueties of vertue to bee done towardes ſtraungers and peregrines. Firſt, we ought to receyue and
<pb facs="tcp:16492:73"/> vſe them, with a Godly and a ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle language, that they may knowe they come to men, and not to cruel &amp; rigorous beaſts. They are not to be ſcoffed and mocked at,<note place="margin">Plautus:</note> wherevpon <hi>Plautus</hi> wryteth in hys Comedy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Penulus: Seruum hercle te eſſe oportet &amp; nequam &amp; malum homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, peregrinum atque aduenam qui irrideas.</hi> Thou muſt nedes be a ſlaue, &amp; an euill and naughtie man, which derideſt a ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Secondly, ſhewing them that which they knowe not in our cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, not to deceyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they are ignorant of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things vſed with vs, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bringeth rather diſpraiſe than prayſe of our countrey, for it is an eaſy thing to beguile the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant.<note place="margin">Eraſmus de inſtr. Prin. Chr.</note> 
                     <hi>Eraſmus</hi> wryteth in his boke <hi>de inſtruc. Prin. Chriſtianoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:74"/> that <hi>Plato</hi> ſhould ſomtyme haue ſayd, that they ought diligenly to reſpect that ſtraungers take no more wrong than Citize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, for that they wanting frendes ſhould ſuffer more wrong. And therfore the Gentiles thought that <hi>Iupiter</hi> was the reuenger of ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers wronges, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Iupiter</hi> for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cauſe <hi>Xontnon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, to ſhewe them the way, when as they ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund it, or be ignorant, not to ſhewe them to take the lefte hande, when as they ſhoulde take the right, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is a moſte wicked fact to bring a ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger out of his way, without our profite, for it is the propertie of a theefe &amp; a prayſeeker to ſhew a ſtraunger willingly a wrong way, whereby he may trappe him in his ſnare, and ſo mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:16492:74" rendition="simple:additions"/> him. Fourthly, to harbour them and ſuffer them to dwell with vs. For which cauſe the Gentiles worſhipped hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie as a holy &amp; ſacred thing, and named <hi>Iupiter</hi> the God of Hoſpitalitie, bycauſe it was a godly and a religious thing to hoſt ſtraungers: And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Dido</hi> Queene of Carthage as <hi>Virgilius</hi> wryteth in his firſt boke of <hi>Eneidos,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Virgilil. li. 1. Aenei.</note> when ſhe recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Eneas</hi> with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other Troia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes into hoſpitalitie, ſhe inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated <hi>Iupiter</hi> in a banquet, as the giuer of meate to geaſtes. And the auncient Romaynes receyued and toke many ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers into their Citie, which in length of tyme were made mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derators and rulers of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.<note place="margin">Li. de vrb. Liuius.</note> As <hi>Liuius</hi> wryteth in his booke <hi>de vrbe condita.</hi> And <hi>Beroal.</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:75"/> ſayth, that in olde tyme pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grines and ſtraungers were more diligent &amp; obedient than Citizens. And that at <hi>Rome</hi> ſtraungers were made great Magiſtrates, counſellers, and Pretors. As in the dayes of <hi>Numa</hi> and <hi>Tarquinius</hi> many pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrines were Counſellers, &amp; they had alſo a ſtraunger Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore which expounded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes to the ſtraungers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Towards our aduerſaries and enimies.</head>
                  <p>WE ought alſo to be ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous towardes our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, &amp; to kepe foure precepts.<note place="margin">Cicero, li. officio.</note> Firſt, as <hi>Cicero</hi> bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs in his boke of Offices. <hi>Etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et fides praeſtita, ſeruanda eſt hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, vt nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o Euquitum lex &amp; couſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudo eſt.</hi> Promiſed fayth ought
<pb facs="tcp:16492:75"/> alſo to be obſerued with thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimie, as the law and cuſtome of Knightes requireth. Who ſo euer be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any and let go, he being called backe againe of the ſame, oughte to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, otherwiſe he ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſed the booke of the noble victorious and ſtout knights. Secondly, if thy aduerſarie or enimy prouoke thee, or wrong thee vniuſtly, or threaten to fighte with thee, thou ought not by and by reue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge and bite againe, for that is the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and nature of brute beaſts. But firſt, indeuour to pacifie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter gently, with frendely frendes, as <hi>Terence</hi> wryteth in <hi>Eunuchus. Omnia prius verbis,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Terentiꝰ</note> 
                     <hi>quam armis experiri ſapientem decet, nihil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que exciſa faciendum improuidè.</hi> A wiſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought to try al things
<pb facs="tcp:16492:76"/> firſt with gentle words, before he fight, neyther ought he to do any thing raſhely and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduiſedly in the heate of his fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Thirdly, if thou be wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged, it is better to forgiue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte that wrong, than to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre wrong againe, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt worthie kinde of reuenging, is to forgiue, &amp; not render like for like.<note place="margin">Eraſmus de inſti. Prin. Chr.</note> 
                     <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in his booke, <hi>de inſtitut. Princ. chriſt.</hi> ſayth: that it denoteth a weake and faynte hearted man to reuenge hys wrong. <hi>Iuuen.</hi> in his .xij. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire, ſayth: that none deſireth more to reuenge than a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. and therefore ſhe ſhall be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of a huſband. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by no meanes we may depell &amp; ſhake off the wrongs of our enimy, vnleſſe we do the like to him againe, then ought
<pb facs="tcp:16492:76" rendition="simple:additions"/> we to immitate that ſaying of <hi>Virgil</hi> in his .xij. boke of <hi>Eneid.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Virg. li. 12. Aeneidos.</note> 
                     <hi>Quo deus &amp; quo dura fortuna ſequa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur.</hi> Let vs try it as it pleaſeth God, and as hard fortune ſhal leade vs. Fortune and vertue are knitte both in one, let vs hardely and boldely reſiſt with weapons as <hi>Liuius</hi> wryteth of the Romane natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: we ought for no other cauſe to fight, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to liue afterwardes in peace, &amp; not to ſeeke reuenge of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Towards our Lordes and Maſters whom we ſerue.</head>
                  <p>WE owe a quadruple re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence towarde our Maſters whoſe breade we eate, and whom we ſerue. Firſt, we ought to be prompt &amp; redy in all things, to obey their
<pb facs="tcp:16492:77"/> precepts and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, not to goe about our buſineſſe creaping like a Snayle, to vſe no ſluggiſhneſſe, take no grefe nor ſlacke our Maſters com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement. Secondly, we ought to be faithful and truſty to them, without deceite, fraud, or guile, not to flatter them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their face, and to ſpeake e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill of them behind their backe. Thirdly, we ought to aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage and profite them, in fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing and auoyding their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commoditie, more to regarde and ſeeke their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moditie and benefite than our owne, ſoner to diſpatch our Maſters buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe than our owne. And if we ſhall ſee our maſter ſuſtaine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny loſſe or hindera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce we ought to auoide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Fourthly, we muſt be mute at two tymes.
<pb facs="tcp:16492:77" rendition="simple:additions"/> Firſt, we muſt not chatte again whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our maſter ſpeaketh, yea &amp; though we ſometimes are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, neyther muſt we alſo be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together dombe: wherevpon <hi>Plaut.</hi> in his comedy of the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſouldier, ſayth:<note place="margin">Plautus.</note> 
                     <hi>Oportet ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uum plus ſcire quam loqui:</hi> It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth a ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to know more than he ſpeaketh. Secondly, he ought to keepe cloſe his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſecretes from other men, and not gaggle them abrode. For taciturnitie greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth a ſeruant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Towards a Magiſtrate.</head>
                  <p>WE owe moreouer a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple duetie to magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; hye Rulers. Firſt, we ought obediently to obey their lawes and ordinances: not to be interrupters of the
<pb facs="tcp:16492:78"/> lawe, but fulfillers of the ſme, for lawes be nothing more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> precepts &amp; documents of well and righteous liuing: neither to repugne nor make inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection againſt them is a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py thing, for the flye getteth nothing by biting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Elephant, neither doth it aduantage the Scarbet to ſeeke the Eagle. Secondly, we ought not to ſlaunder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neyther by word, nor by deede: for he ſpeaketh not ſafely nor yet wryteth not ſurely, which ſpeaketh or wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth againſt thoſe which haue power and authoritie to binde and condemne him. Neyther is it a decent thing, to ſting or hurt them whoſe ſtudy and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is night and day to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, defend, and vertuouſly to moderate the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon weale.
<pb facs="tcp:16492:78" rendition="simple:additions"/> Thirdly, if they ſhall require a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny trybute, ye ought gently to giue them, for by that meanes Regions &amp; Cities are defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, maintayned, and vpholded, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the flouriſhing floure would ſone fade away and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.<note place="margin">Liuius. lib. 2.</note> For as <hi>Liuius</hi> wryteth in his ſecond booke: <hi>De Vrbe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dita. Si coetera corporis membra ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macho cibum no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuppeditarent, ſimul cum ipſo fame perire<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> If the other members and parts of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhould not help the ſtomack with meate, they ſhould toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther periſhe with the ſtomacke for hunger. So likewiſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Citizens &amp; Inhabitants of the Citie helpe the Princes and Magiſtrates of the ſame with faculties and mony, they ſhal together be ouercome and ſlaine with their Prince.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:16492:79"/>
               <head>¶ What is decent at all tymes and places.</head>
               <head>The fourth Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the vſage of honeſtie, and none otherwiſe of vertue place and time are much to be regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: of the which two reſpects except reaſon in the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of Principalitie, beare ſway, nothing, (or at the leaſt) very little, ſhall the knowledge of vertue, or practiſing of the ſame profite at all. For the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Theologians, interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the diuine Scriptures, make mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſinnes and hainous offences are by place and time, aggrauate; and alſo eaſed by the ſame. To the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of theſe two, or as it were
<pb facs="tcp:16492:79" rendition="simple:additions"/> borders adioyning honeſtie or vertue, ſpecially be adiected. For in dyuers places, dyuers and ſtraunge things are to be frequented, as decent, fitte, and lawfull. Which if they be not to any knowen, or very few immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, although they haue bene ſtudents in the ſchole of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, yet as vicious perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhall they be imputed, if by ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce howe, in tyme, and place, to behaue themſelues doe bleare their drouſie eyes. Therefore <hi>Macrobius. lib. 7. Saturn.</hi> ſayth: No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more nigh vnto wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, than to fitte our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication in conuenient place or tyme. Alſo <hi>Pytacus Mytil.</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded tyme to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, that whatſoeuer we did practiſe to finiſh, firſt, we ſhould ſee the oportunitie of tyme, for
<pb facs="tcp:16492:80"/> he eſtemed or ſuppoſed that to be the beſt in any matter. And herevpon <hi>Terence</hi> ſayd.<note place="margin">Terentius</note> I came in ſeaſon which is the chiefeſt poynt of all. But howe a man may according to the prouerb, be <hi>Omnium horarum homo,</hi> theſe wordes following will openly manifeſt and declare.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ What maner of the honeſtie at ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketting is required.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Laces and tymes are dyuers wherin men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, aſſemble or talke, but eſpecially y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place or time of banketting, if ſo be that at the leaſt any geaſt appointed be there preſent. For it is no leſſe hurte than damage to all men, to pamper the belly, or to liue immoderately, as a man might ſay at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feaſt of dronken
<pb facs="tcp:16492:80" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                     <hi>Bacchus,</hi> as one of hys typpled Prelates.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Sixe honeſt or vertuous precepts, worthy at Meales to be imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and obſerued.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt obſeruation as <hi>Macrobiꝰ</hi> ſayth <hi>lib. 7.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Macrobius.</note> 
                     <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalium</hi>) is to eſteme, pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or thinke by the geaſtes as they be, meaning of what ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, what dignitie or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie. The ſecond (as the ſame <hi>Macrobius</hi> relateth,) is for euery man, to ſee when place is fitte, or conuenient, not to talke or commen of Philoſophie, at ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes prepared, with ſuſtinance to refreſh the body. Therefore <hi>Socrates</hi> at a certaine tyme,<note place="margin">Socrates.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing demaunded at a banket, that he would manifeſt ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by communication, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered:
<pb facs="tcp:16492:81"/> I knowe not thoſe things which preſent time and place requireth, and the ſame which I am not ignorant in, are not decent as nowe to be vttered, ſuppoſing that thoſe graue queſtions whereof the Philoſophers reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſchole, be not fitte at bankets, as ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ketting diſhes to be ſerued.</p>
                  <p>Thirdely, they are called for ſtrife or contention rather, yea, it ſoner aryſeth, by quaffing or canuaſſing, of the pots, than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny otherwyſe at all. Fourthly, let there be a meane obſerued in eating or drinking, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theſe two precepts, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay: let thy meate be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken without gluttonie, and thy drinke without ebrietle. Fifth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Plautus</note> theſe ſeuen precepts of <hi>Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus comoed. Militis glorioſi.</hi> Euery
<pb facs="tcp:16492:81" rendition="simple:additions"/> man muſt imitate. Let him be, no cauiller, a profitable geaſt, no tatler, obſtinent from all diſcomoditie, a ſpeaker at due tyme, a keper of quiet, till ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declare his fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſie, a ſmall interrupter of mennes talke, no buſie demaunder of queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Sixtly, let him not be an opener or blaſer abroade of things, ſpoken, hearde, ſeene, or done. Therefore <hi>Horace</hi> in hys ſixt Epiſtle, calling a greaſt <hi>Foro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum,</hi> promiſeth that he would take charge, that there ſhould be none at the banket, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would declare any thing without the Threſhald of the dore. And <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roaldus,</hi> declareth, that it was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuſtome of certaine Gentiles, their appointed geaſt entring their houſe, to ſhewe to them their Threſhald, ſaying: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:16492:82"/> this is there nothing, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, take heede how you vtter thoſe things abrode, which you heare at the table: wherfore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in our time this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faſhion, to haue Roſes painted aboue or ouer the table, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnder them our communications at repaſt, might be kept, and not ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red any other where.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ How to behaue our ſelues in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſober company.</head>
                  <p>IT is no ſmall cunning, nay rather a great and egregious wiſedome, to knowe howe profitably to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue our ſelues among men, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by our familiaritie we may pleaſe others, &amp; ſo to retaine our mutuall friends. Which thinges to bring to paſſe we had nede of .vij. eſpecial docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:16492:82" rendition="simple:additions"/> Firſt, let vs acuſtom our ſelues to beare &amp; ſuffer the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, words, &amp; deedes of men, &amp; not by &amp; by to ſound the dogs letter. R. as though we would byte (if to vs any damage they inferre) but as witting no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the ſame, let vs ſeeme to winke. For to be ſnapping &amp; ſnarring, or at the leaſt, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry at a ſmall offence, is the pointe or manyfeſt token of a weake man, not able to brydle his owne nature. Secondly, let vs ſubſcribe to their arby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trement &amp; ſentence, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and nilling might be vnto vs with them, that is to ſay, to conſent to that which they doe require, &amp; eſchew thoſe things which are not good, but rather lurke as miſchieuous baytes, to enta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gle the vnwary. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:83"/> to be obedient to their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, works and indeuouring, as diligent Students of that diſcipline or learning, which they imitate. For where the peſtiferous diſcention of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes hath a reſting place, there in a ſhorte moment, the ſhrill conuict is ſong. Fourthly, let vs not hate vnworthily any man, in proferring of ſtrife or iniury, either by mocking wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, or wicked communicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Fifthly, let vs preſume before no man, thoughe we be their betters, of more abilitie in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance or treaſure. Let vs not hinder them, for aſmuch conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering we would not take it in good part, to be hindered our ſelues. Sixtly, we muſt be eaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly intreated, and readily gyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that where ſoeuer tyme or
<pb facs="tcp:16492:83" rendition="simple:additions"/> place require, we may ſhew ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe to other. For,<note place="margin">Terentiꝰ</note> 
                     <hi>Obſequiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> parit amicos, intermiſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inimicos pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perit ſemper.</hi> The other maners and rytes, dayly vſe and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience which is the miſtreſſe of things doth teach.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ In mutuall or frendly communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, <hi>praeceptiunculae.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the frendely talke or communication of men, there are eight precepts or rules of vertue, as neceſſary to be imitated. Not to trouble other mennes communicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to refrayne thy tong from ſpeach, and haue a regarde to the concluſion of their words. And herevpon aroſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prouerbe. Two may ſing but not be vnderſtand: for the talke of the one hindreth the
<pb facs="tcp:16492:84"/> ſpeach of the other, that it can not be fully percieued. To take away no mans honour, either abſent or preſent: for there is no thefte greater, no robberie worſer, than the taking away of a mannes fame. Nothing hath he to vſe after life &amp; death but fame, which once being fleted,<note place="margin">Ouid.</note> as <hi>Ouid</hi> ſayth, afterward he is nothing (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is) of no eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation or effect. We ought to haue a regard what we ſpeake of any man, leaſt ſome being preſent at our talke, receyue dammage thereby, eſpecially oure frendes or familliar ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance. We may vtter no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, whether it be a fond tale or wyſe talke, hauing before our eyes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may as well hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as profite. Let euery man therfore take hede how to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:16492:84" rendition="simple:additions"/> of any new matters, or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, leaſt he be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted (as you may tearme him) the loder of long tongue Mill. For he that as a newe vpſtart medleth in euery mans caſe, is iudged a trifling marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, fighting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the enſigne of the lying ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. Make not inquiſition vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon other mennes ſecretes, for two cauſes. The firſt is, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſtandeth yll with thoſe oftentymes whoſe ſecretes are knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The ſecond, inſomuch that the demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders or queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aſkers, be iudged betrayers or (ſecrets once knowen) bewrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the ſame, wherby y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd might ſuſtaine a maruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous detrime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Whether a man be ſober or dronken, as witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>Horatius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Horatius.</note> let him keepe hys owne counſell, for vttering his
<pb facs="tcp:16492:85"/> inward thoughtes, he is iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged worſer than a theefe. For ſecretes oft tymes performe a confeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe things which be proloyned by latrones or euill diſpoſed perſonnes, none will ſpeake thinges but eyther vnderſtode or knowen, except he be a backbyter, or ſome falſe tatling Sycophant.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Whilſt we be in talking with an honeſt name, how to behaue our ſelues.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ERaſmus</hi> in his booke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled <hi>Colloquia</hi> ſayth. As often as any man ſpeaketh vnto thee, to whome thou oweſt honour or reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, frame thy ſelf to the right ſtate of thy body, with cap in hande, thy countenace indifferent, neither ſadly nor fleringly, but
<pb facs="tcp:16492:85" rendition="simple:additions"/> keping the meane of modeſtie, thine eies chaſt, alwayes fixed vpon him to whom thou ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt, thy feete cloſe together, thy handes not buſie, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes quiet, not wauering w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tattering feete, nor trifling with thy fingers, neyther by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thy lippes, ſcratching thy heade, or picking thyne eares. Alſo let thy garmentes comely adorne thy body, that thy reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, thy countinance, thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour &amp; apparelling of thy body might declare a notable modeſtie and chaſt diſpoſition of thy minde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ In walking abrode with others: a certaine note or onſeruation.</head>
                  <p>IF it happen, or chaunce that we walke abrode or ſoiourne with any man,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:86"/> it is neceſſary and conuenient that we be decked as it were with nine maners. Firſt, cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in communication, ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle or eaſy to be ſpoken with: for <hi>Plautus</hi> ſaith, that a pleaſant co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the way is as it were a Chariot, eaſing the weary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our iourney. If we be in dignitie inferior, we muſt go on the lefte ſyde, or elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde, &amp; not cheeke by cheeke, except that good leaue or ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence be permitted. Likewiſe we muſt not vſe an ouer ſwift paſe, but a decent and tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate feſtination,<note place="margin">Cicero in Officiis.</note> as <hi>Cicero in Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiis</hi> willeth vs. In going of a iourney, or from place to place, let vs not commacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late oure wayfaring compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, but lette vs ſo moderate our feete and foote ſteps, that
<pb facs="tcp:16492:86" rendition="simple:additions"/> we ſprinkle not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other with mudde or dirty baggage. Let vs ſpeake with a lowe voyce, &amp; not with a boſting tong. Let vs honour whom we meete by the way, in giuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hande, and by other mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes wherby reuerence is exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, ſaluting obuied perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, for it is a ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle, a laudable and Godly point.<note place="margin">Cato.</note> Therefore <hi>Cato</hi> once ſaid: <hi>Saluta libenter.</hi> Salute euery man willingly. For ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is none other thing, than to wiſh health, or good ſucceſſe to any man. Alſo let vs put off our Cappes, and vncouer oure heades, whiche is a manifeſt ſigne of humbling our ſelues, and acknoweledging that we be inferiours to the foreſayde, which Chriſt commaunded vs, to appeare, I meane humble
<pb facs="tcp:16492:87"/> and not luſty in mynd &amp; heart.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ How to behaue our ſelues in a proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous ſtrate or tyme.</head>
                  <p>TIme alſo requireth his comelineſſe or good v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, for eyther by time we offend more or leſſe. Tyme is double, eyther that is to ſay, merry or proſperous, elſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy, ſorrowfull, or infortunate. Time, if it be lucky, or bleſſed, a quadruple comlyneſſe is to be obſerued. Firſt of all not to boaſt to highe, &amp; reioyce whilſt fortune laugheth at oure ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, which was wonte to be done among the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon people as <hi>Iuuenal</hi> alleageth. <hi>Neſcia mens hominum rebus modum ſeruare ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundis.</hi> exhorting that the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant minde of men not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what would happen here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:87" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhould obſerue a merry meane in their proſperitie.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, not to mocke &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe him before vs, as though we were happier than he who fortune frowneth againſt. For this boaſting and glorying in minde, is that which is moſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of God. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to feare &amp; alwayes be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, leaſt fortune lowringly ſhould be mutable or changed with vs. For ſhe is more vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant than the winde, and is ſayde to ſtande on a turning wheele, ſo that ſhe can not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in one ſtate. Therefore in tymes paſt a certaine Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher waxed very ſorrowfull in his richeſt ſtate, knowing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter proſperitie, aduerſitie ſhuld aryſe. In this miſerable eſtate he reioyced, ſurely perſwading
<pb facs="tcp:16492:88"/> him ſelfe, that after ſhowers, fayre weather ſhould enſue, &amp; after his penſiueneſſe greate ioy and mirth ſhould followe. Fourthly, giuing thanks vnto God for his great beneuolence beſtowed on vs, that we may not be vnthankefull, but by our humilitie ſtirre him vp to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe vs the more: Let vs not forget God, for the felicitie of fortune, as rich me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were wont. and dayly I feare me doe, but let vs remember him, pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him with thankefull minds, that he might multiplie and more proſper the frendly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of fortune, which he hath beſtowed vpon vs, or elſe ende the ſame by any indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent meane.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:88" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>¶ In the tyme of aduerſitie.</head>
                  <p>BVt if that tyme be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſt wyth cloudes and ſorrowfull, let vs be ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med or munited with ſixe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes. Firſt of all, let vs ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer diſcomfort our minde, as though hereafter we might not be more fortunate or happie, but let vs hope with a valiant minde for better chaunce, and comforte our ſelues with thys ſaying of <hi>Virgil,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Virgil.</note> 
                     <hi>Dabit Deus his quoque finem.</hi> God will finiſhe theſe our troubles and calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Secondly, let vs ſeke cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to remedie this infelicitie, eyther by our owne witte, or elſe by the prudent aduiſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Thirdly, let vs be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, of God, humbly makyng our Oriſon vnto him, and not
<pb facs="tcp:16492:89"/> curſſing his deitie for the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie which we ſuffer, but that he would vouchſafe that trouble not long to continue, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow his grace vpon vs, to our ſaluation, that we may take in good part any croſſe which he ſhall lay vpon vs. Fourthly, we ought to reioyce, rather than to be ſory, that the ſame aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie hath light vpon vs, by the which at the hands of god, we may deſerue, to haue rewarde &amp; be deliuered from our ſinnes. Fifthly, we muſt vphold, or as it were vnderproppe our mind with a good hope, as if we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred iuſtly puniſhment for our offences, ſaying with the Poet <hi>Ouid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Quae venit ex merito, poena ferenda venit.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Ouidius.</note>
                        <hi>Quae venit indigne spoena dolonda venit.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16492:89" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>That puniſhment that iuſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth,</l>
                     <l>is not to repented:</l>
                     <l>But that vnworthily doth happe,</l>
                     <l>is much to be lamented.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Sixtly we muſt conſider our ſelues to be me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, fighting vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enſigne of fortitude, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a great ſhame to be feared with euery ſhadowe of aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ In ſeruing and obeying others.</head>
                  <p>IN performing obeyſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, it behoueth vs to be wiſe and ſage, that our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice might be acceptable vnto thoſe, on whom it is beſtowed, leaſt our diligence and trauail be laughed to ſcorne: for there are ſixe notes to be obſerued. We muſt prouide, that our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice be profitable, vnto whom it is offered. For he that giueth hurtfull obeyſance exhibiteth
<pb facs="tcp:16492:90"/> no frendſhip but rather deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, let it be done in due ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or time:<note place="margin">Eraſmus.</note> for as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth, benefites out of ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are the leſſe to be regarded. And likewyſe herevnto is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prouerbe replied. <hi>Charè co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtat prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus quod emitur.</hi> That benefite is deare, which is bought with the penny. Deferre not to fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh therefore good turnes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted, and eſpecially already promiſed. For tardineſſe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of tyme, maketh frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip vnthankfull. Therefore, willingly, if thou haue buſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in hand ſpeedily to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teſt a frend, finiſh the ſame with all celeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, leaſt thou be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrained, as in tymes paſt the Aſſe was, to drinke vnwillingly: or accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the prouerbe, trifle, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb facs="tcp:16492:90" rendition="simple:additions"/> at the man in the Moone to no effect at all. The buſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our friende ought to be done, as faithfully as our own, for herein the bright beames of friendſhip is declared. For Offices are eſteemed lyke as the will of the performer, and the thankes of a former bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite periſheth, except it be renu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an other.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ The office or duetie of a Magiſtrate.</head>
                  <p>IF we beare the prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence of a Magiſtrate, &amp; dominate ouer others, as rulers and gouernours of them; it is neceſſarie that eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially we abounde in foure ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall points of wiſedome. Let vs behaue our ſelues, as we would euery man ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde
<pb facs="tcp:16492:91"/> vs: let vs be wyſer than the reſt ouer whome we beare ſway. For it is a filthie thing to be a ſuperiour in honour, &amp; not in wiſedome. By the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of the Magiſtrates au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, let vs not with preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous mindes deſpiſe other, playing <hi>Millitem illu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Terentianu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> But let vs followe this ſaying of <hi>Cicero,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> the higher we be, the lower to ſubmit our ſelues, lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> commoditie of others more than to our owne: for a Magiſtrate is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not a priuate. Let vs not hurt the innocent nor fauour the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, but in puniſhment let there be a meane, according to the fault,<note place="margin">Cicero.</note> as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſayth. Let the rulers be like vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes which proceede with equitie &amp; iuſtice, to puniſh the mal<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.
<pb facs="tcp:16492:91" rendition="simple:additions"/> Let vs haue a regarde to puniſh theſe ten vyces from our common weales, <hi>perfidia, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culatus, auaritia, inuidia, ambitio, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trectatio, periuriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, indilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia, iniuria, &amp; ſcelus,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plautus.</note> as <hi>Plautus</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth <hi>in Per. Comoe.</hi> Let vs thinke that many other things do become vs, than thoſe ouer whom we beare ſway, &amp; that our faults be ſoner ſpyed tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the faults of our ſubiects, as learned Poets in tymes paſt haue ſong.</p>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="poem">
                              <head>Ouidius in Conſo. ad Liuiam.</head>
                              <l>Non eadem vulguſ<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> decent &amp; lumina reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
                              <l>Est quod praecipuum debeas ista domus.☜</l>
                              <l>Ad cocilos aureſ<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> trabis, tua facta notamꝰ</l>
                              <l>Ned vamiſsa poteſt, Principis ere tegi.</l>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                        <body>
                           <div type="poem">
                              <head>Claudianus.</head>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Hoc te praeterea crebro ſermone monebo,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Vt te totius medio telluris is in orbe,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Viuere cognoſcas, cunctis tua, gentibus eſse</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Facta palam, nec poſse dari, regalibus vſquam</hi>
                              </l>
                              <pb facs="tcp:16492:92"/>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Secretum vitijs, nam lux altiſsima fati,</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Occultum nil eſse ſinit, latebraſ<expan>
                                       <am>
                                          <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                       </am>
                                       <ex>que</ex>
                                    </expan> per omneis</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Intrat, &amp; abstruſos explorat fama receſsus.</hi>
                              </l>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="poem">
                              <l>The chairie charge of Conſulſhip</l>
                              <l>eche wight doth well beholde:</l>
                              <l>Like as the Caruers workmanſhip,</l>
                              <l>adornd with fulgent golde.</l>
                              <l>And therefore had the Magiſtrate</l>
                              <l>néede for to rule his land:</l>
                              <l>The fectiue braunch to diſſecate,</l>
                              <l>with equall ſworde in hand.</l>
                              <l>The ſubiectes eyes on him do blaſe</l>
                              <l>they liſten in his talke:</l>
                              <l>In this reſpect he néede alwayes</l>
                              <l>vprightly for to walke.</l>
                              <l>For openly his faſtes are knowen</l>
                              <l>no lurking place they finde:</l>
                              <l>His geffes through vapored ayres are blowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              </l>
                              <l>the Commons be not blind.</l>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:16492:92" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ How vertue or honeſtie being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opted ought to be vſed, that it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer might fléete againe.</head>
               <head>The fifth Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat vertue and honeſtie once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, might not depart, &amp; we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by led aſtray, thre precepts fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing are to be graue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in our breaſt, or inſculped in our min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, that as a key or anker, thei might retaine to vs vertue, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh honeſtie, and ratifie good maners. Firſt of all, we muſt take heede of all things, which oppreſſe or kepe downe probi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, we muſt flee all the intice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of vyces, all pleaſures &amp; wicked diliciouſneſſe, as ryot &amp; ydleneſſe. Herevpon <hi>Hermo Bar.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:93"/> ſayd: He that will imitate ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, muſt flye the belly God &amp; the Harlot <hi>Venus.</hi> Secondly, we muſt thinke vpon nothing, neyther do any thing but that which is honeſt or nighe vnto vertue, onely let honeſt things be exerciſed and put in prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe. In a good matter or thing let all our worke be, all our labour, &amp; all our thought. So at the laſt ſhall it come to paſſe, that we may be accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with vertue, no leſſe than if it were graffed in vs, hating vice as a Dogge or a peſtilent Serpent.<note place="margin">Virgil.</note> Herevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Virgil</hi> ſpake ſaying: it is a great thing to be from our infancie accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with vertue. Nothing is of more effect, than dayly vſe. Thirdly, peraduenture a man would ſay, who can indeuour
<pb facs="tcp:16492:93"/> to meditate honeſt cauſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, but ſomtyme he muſt play <hi>Dormiter Homerus,</hi> conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that no man is wyſe at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſeaſon. Therefore this thirde precept is to be embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with hand and foote, with tooth and nayle, that is to ſay, to banquet, or communicate with honeſt men, not ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting by ſeduction our ſelues from their companie, as <hi>Cicero</hi> wryteth that he neuer depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Mutius Scoeuola</hi> an olde man. For it is a maruellous thing to be ſpoken howe much the domeſticall or quotidian familiaritie of men auayle in manets, that almoſt it chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth and inuerteth, nay, alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether varieth the nature of man: Therefore the Pſalmiſt Dauid wryteth:<note place="margin">Dauid</note> 
                  <hi>Cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bono bonus
<pb facs="tcp:16492:94"/> eris, &amp; cum malo peruerteris.</hi> With the good thou ſhalt wax good, and with the wicked thou ſhalt learne wickedneſſe. Therefore we ſhall be honeſt and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, as long as we be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſant with good perſons, and liue in ſuch a Godly order.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:16492:94" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ Howe a man may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the chiefe pointes of Chriſtianitie, or deduction of a Chriſtian life.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Of what maner the inſtitution of the firſt age ought to be.</head>
               <p>THe part of a Father, is to bring his child into the ſchole, (the time of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie beeing paſt, &amp; growen to the full perfection of ſeauen yeares) to procede and go for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde in learning, if he couet to haue him good, being fleſh of his owne bodie, and not a wanton, as the common pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents do nowe a dayes noſſell their children vp. Therefore in tyme teach him modeſtie, pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per him not vppe with trifling
<pb facs="tcp:16492:95"/> toyes, but keepe hym vnder with the rod of correction, that he may frame his lyfe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the preſcribed rule of the ſyncere veritie or worde of God. Let him be puniſhed if he offend: let him be prayſed, if he behaue him ſelfe well and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly: with threatning &amp; ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, let him be feared from vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: by exhortations, let him be progged to vertue: yea, and let the patrone haue a greater regarde, to the maners of edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his childe than the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his own bodily health: Let him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit him to teachers, graue, ſage &amp; wittie, learned, quiet and vertuous, where he might taſt of the pleaſant fruit of learning, &amp; ſweete lyquours of the Latine ſpeach: Let him beſtowe his tyme on thoſe ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deis,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:95" rendition="simple:additions"/> which inſtruct the minde with precepts and docume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Among the which is Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie. This Nurſſe alone ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a better nature of a good, a chaſt nature of a wicked, and eaſier to be intreated. Let a Chriſtian accuſtome him ſelfe, and learne that God muſt firſt be honoured as the wel ſpring from whome all good things haue their iſſue: let him learne to obey reaſon, and follow hir in all the conuerſation of hys lyfe, as his chiefe capitaine and gouernour in worde and dede. Let him couet or doe nothing, but that which is honeſt and right. Let him alſo brydle his cogitations, the ſecretes whereof god the iudge of all heartes wyll peruſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:16492:96"/>
               <head>¶ God to be gratified of good men, and to puniſh the wicked.</head>
               <p>DOeſt thou thinke that righteouſnes is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſight of God, and doeſt thou worſhip him as the Lord and maker of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and earth, doeſt thou prayſe his name day and night: that thereby thou mighteſt deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite the ſight of him, by good &amp; iuſt workes? Doubt nothing, but as he is able, ſo he can, and will gratifie thee. For what is ſo agreable vnto him, as bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence? and againe, what is more alienate or ſtraunge, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnthankfulneſſe? Therefore leaſt any ſhould accuſe him as vnthankefull, which liue god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he beſtoweth his grace on them, as he letteth his anger
<pb facs="tcp:16492:96" rendition="simple:additions"/> droppe vpon wicked perſons, adulterers, whooremongers, robbers &amp; manſlaughterers. And when he ſeeth that there is no ende of ſinning, he ary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth at the laſt, to take puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the rebellious people, and blotteth out the wicked or hurtfull.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Certaine anger righteous, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and neceſſarie.</head>
               <p>IF the ſeruants, children, or diſciples, learners I meane, whome we haue vnder gouernment, offend, we are angrie reforme them, we cry vpon them to amende, we brydle them wyth correction, to make them good. This an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is no ſinne: for that which is wicked, doth much diſpleaſe a good man, and whom leud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb facs="tcp:16492:97"/> doeth grieue, he is much moued, if he ſee any offende. Therefore the father ryſeth vp to auenge. The mayſter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth rods to be in a redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, not that he mindeth to hurte, but that he might prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe diſcipline, correct euiil ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and ſuppreſſe to much ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſnes. God vſeth this iuſt diſpleaſure to ſubdue men and ſinners, rewarding their wicked eſtate.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The refraining of anger on ſinnes, to be vicious.</head>
               <p>THey are greatly to bee reprehended which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay their diſpleaſure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the wickednes of their vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and oftener than nedes pardon their faults. By ſuch like whether they be fathers,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:97" rendition="simple:additions"/> whether they be rulers or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, the lyfe of the offender is loſt, by whoſe lenitie out of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or tyme, vnbrydled youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full age is nouriſhed, and they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues which haue ſo ſmall a regarde, miniſter a great bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued heape of griefe. Here ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we muſt not refrain from anger, but alſo if it be throwen downe, we haue occaſion to ſtirre it vp againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ That we muſt giue an accompt of our tyme ſpent.</head>
               <p>LEt euery man make an accompt of thoſe things which he hath receyued, which he hath expe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced, bicauſe many an ydle worde hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcaped hym. Whatſoeuer we heare of others, we ought to let it flye as it were by the gates
<pb facs="tcp:16492:98"/> of our eares. For there be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine precepts or rules of the tongue to be marked, ſo that the words which we vtter, firſt come into the entrie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mind, before the mouth devulgate the ſame. Our ſtomacke muſt after ſuche a rate be pacified, that no opprobrious or wicked thing ſhoote out therof. And if any thing be inwardly ſprong vp, by and by it is our part, by earneſt ſtudy, and ſerious toile to plucke vppe the ſame by the rootes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Certain neceſſaries to be prepared in the trauailing towarde the life to come.</head>
               <p>AS they which trauail in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a farre cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey, a little before they goe thither, prepare or ſcracth together co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient
<pb facs="tcp:16492:98" rendition="simple:additions"/> thinges for their iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, leaſt they ſhould periſhe through hunger by the way, ſo ought we to prouide in the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this lyfe, we muſt lay vppe the treaſure of good workes, of righteouſneſſe, of humilitie, of continencie, and of all other vertues, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> at what tyme, day or houre, God ſhall call vs, to trauayle to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Paradice our Countrey, we might be found ready.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ In this life we muſt waſh away the filthineſſe of our ſinnes.</head>
               <p>MY Chriſtian brother, waſhe away thy ſinne by confeſſion. For he that refuſeth in thys tyme to pourge him ſelfe from hys ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, afterward he ſhall not finde conſolation at the hande
<pb facs="tcp:16492:99"/> of God. For after death who ſhall confeſſe the Lorde? Here we muſt make a bickerment, here we muſt ſtryue, leaſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paying day of the labourers hyre, we be counted as vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſeruantes, and ſo ſeclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the face of the Lorde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ We muſt flée.</head>
               <p>IF thou exerciſe or prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe vertue, other men ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame, they wyll not onely prayſe thee, but glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie God which is in heauen. When they ſhall do ſo, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſtore ſhall increaſe, and God ſhal grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto thee thy harts deſire, bicauſe that by thy good workes, he is prayſed of them. Therfore ſtudie alwayes, that thou be not an occaſion of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending to any perſon. Paule
<pb facs="tcp:16492:99" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſayde. <hi>Si cibus offenderit fratrem meum, nunquam in aeternum carnem comedam.</hi> If meate ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende my brother, I would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer eate any.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The workes of learning, or tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching muſt be ioyned with déedes.</head>
               <p>NO man ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented in him ſelfe. For God will alſo, that we edifie others, not by teaching onely, but in lyfe, in maners and conuerſation. Men couet rather examples than words, they doe not ſo greatly marke the things that we ſpeake, as the things we doe. Good ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings or inſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcholes doe not ſo profite, as thoſe things hurte, which wickedly we do. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> affirmeth wordes
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:100"/> nay bleſſed are we, ſwimming only in that port, free from tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, voide of care &amp; poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing an euerlaſting reſt, which Chriſt him ſelfe foreſhewed to come, ſaying: <hi>A me diſcite, quia mitis ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; humilis corde, &amp; inuenietis requiem animabus veſtris.</hi> Learne of me bicauſe I am gentle and humble in heart, and you ſhall finde reſt to your ſoules.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe they ſhould do, that are not able to faſt.</head>
               <p>CAnſt thou not faſt? Deale more liberally to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, be feruenter in prayers to god, ſhew thy ſelfe more readie to heare the diuine myſteries &amp; holy ſermons or exhortations. Haſt thou an enemie? doe thy diligence to be reconciled. See y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou remoue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy mind all
<pb facs="tcp:16492:100" rendition="simple:additions"/> hatred or gredy deſire of aue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, imbracing gentleneſſe or lenitie. To this ende faſting is appointed, that the laſciuiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the fleſhe being refray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, we might ſpeedily runne as it were to fulfyll the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ What miſchiefe Gluttonie cauſeth.</head>
               <p>COueteſt thou to haue thy health? it behoueth thee then to flee ſumptuous ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, &amp; to much gluttonie. For hereof aryſeth the Goute, the headeache, and the ſuperfluitie of peſtilent humors. Intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and to much ſwilling of wine, breadeth innumerable kindes of diſeaſes</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The goodneſſe that aryſeth of confeſſion.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16492:101"/>
               <p>HAſt thou deſfloured a vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin? haſt thou commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted adulterie or any ſuch like? Haſten to the confeſſion of thy ſinne. Go to the Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he may looke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſoule, and heale thy grieuous diſeaſes. Here receyue reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: ſpeake to thy ſelfe alone. Say, why haſt thou offended? For the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoſe things wherewith we haue grieuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offended God, aboliſheth our offences. Attend vnto the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, ſaying. <hi>Dic tu prior iniquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes tuas, vt iuſtificeris.</hi> Shew thou firſt thine iniquities, that thou mayſt be iuſtified.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The regard of the ſoule, not to haue ſo much tending to, as the body.</head>
               <p>THe charge of the ſoule is light and eaſy, for we ſpende nothing that it
<pb facs="tcp:16492:101" rendition="simple:additions"/> might haue hir health. On the contrarie parte, if the body be ſicke, what coſt do we beſtow? now vpon Phiſitians, now v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon other things, which we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume or waſte more tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neede requireth. The ſoule hath none of theſe, vnto the which, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Scriptures, is as meate, clothing, ſuccour, or al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. For the orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we decke our bodyes, be not dayly prayers, confeſſion of ſinnes with teares, but pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous exceſſe in clothing, &amp; ſuch like vanitie of the world. Early in the morning we apparel vs, we waſhe oure face, leaſt any ſpecke ſhould cleaue on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. If all this be done for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the body, with how great a regard, ought the ſoule to be waſhed, that we might of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb facs="tcp:16492:102"/> it louing, and beautiful vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lorde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Who is worthie to be called a man.</head>
               <p>NOt he which ſheweth a faire countenance, hys noſetrilles, his eye lids, and the other members of his body, that is giuen vnto vertue, flying vyces, and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the commaundements of the Lorde, him mayſt thou call a man. The worde of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priueth a ſinner, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of man, than the which offender nothing is more miſerable.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Giuing of thankes to be much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to our lyfe.</head>
               <p>NOthing can be more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto god, than dayly giuing of tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:102" rendition="simple:additions"/> for ſo many benefites, which his gentleneſſe hath beſtowed on mankind. The voyce of the Apoſtle is: be thankfull, be not thoſe benefites commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to thee which he hath beſtowed vpon all men? Therfore gratifie his name. For the remembrance of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefites of Chriſt, is a good ſcholemiſtres to ſhew vs howe we ought to frame our life. For ſhe doth not ſuffer vs to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſluggiſhneſſe, and imitate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked-mans practiſe. By this reaſon man differeth from the brute beaſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, to prayſe, cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate, and glorifie the Lord, the onely maker, creator and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioner of al things. Great are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gifts which he hath beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon vs. He hath giuen vs body and ſoule, ſheepe &amp; oxen, with all the Cattell of the field.
<pb facs="tcp:16492:103"/> Prophets hath he ſent which might inſtruct vs, and correct mannes wickedneſſe. Finally, euerie kind of mortall creature waxing worſſe &amp; worſſe, wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe being ſpred abrode, &amp; that which is moſt odious, the worſhipping of Idolles, he tooke compaſſion vpon man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, &amp; ſent his onely begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſonne into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, to take vpon him mannes nature, and appeare to the iuſtification of ſinners. Let vs therfore think day and night vpon the great benefites of God, beſtowed on vs, yelding perpetuall thankes vnto him for the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Ebrietie is wicked.</head>
               <p>DRonkenneſſe blyndeth mans ſenſes and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, drowneth his mind, and forceth the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:16492:103" rendition="simple:additions"/> creature to lye deade, as a trunck or blocke, vnto whom God hath made al things ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. In the meane ſeaſon he is mocked of all men, as well his wife, his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the reſt of his houſholde. His friendes ſuppoſing thys a diſſehonour, drawe themſelues aſyde. They that be wicked perſons, or hys enimies reioyce, laugh him to ſcorne, and curſſe him, tearme him hog or ſwine, or ſuch lyke beaſtly name, diſdayning him, and working him all the iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie they may.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ A ſempeternall name is not gotten in great buildings.</head>
               <p>WYth how great a deſire nowe a dayes, doe our Senators, Magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Gouernours of the Citie. Lordes, Biſhops, and ſuch like,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:104"/> builde gorgious houſes, lyke vnto the Pallaces of Kinges. If thou aſke them, why they beſtowe ſo great coſte, why they lay out ſuch aboundance of treaſure? this is their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. That they might leaue behinde the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to their ſucceſſors, ſome memoriall ſigne or toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the paſſers by might ſay, This houſe he builded. Thys cunning, or workemanſhippe was made of his coſt. O foliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, O cares of men, howe great vanitie is there in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance? By this cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell, by this iudgement, they building after ſuch ſort, purchaſe themſelues no prayſe, as they ſuppoſe, but rather a great diſhonour. For theſe wordes are bruted of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, being yet aliue, as after their diſceaſſe. To builde this houſe,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:104" rendition="simple:additions"/> theſe Gates, that couetous ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that rauener, that deuourer or ſpoyler of the comfortleſſe wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, hath taken charge. Do they get a name by this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? or do they wrappe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in eternall reproche? Iudge ye. If this be their one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care, I will ſhewe them an other way howe to poſſeſſe the ſame. They muſt ſtudy to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow vpon the poore that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or ſubſtance which was prepared to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> building of vaſte places. By this benignitie, by this compaſſion, they ſhall get vnto them a ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>piternal prayſe, &amp; being deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous burthen of their ſinnes, poſſeſſe with God, in the glory of his kingdome, a crowne of pure gold, neuer fading or tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie, but for euer perpetuall.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:16492:105"/>
               <head>¶ Ambition is a daungerous thing.</head>
               <p>THou whiche followeſt Chriſt, and takeſt him for thy maſter, couet not the higheſt place, but be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the ſaying of S. Paule, <hi>Honore alius alium praecedentes, date operam, vt in omnibus humiliemini.</hi> One of you excelling an other in honour, take heede that you be humble in all poyntes. For the worde of God ſayth. <hi>Qui ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum humiliat, exaltabitur.</hi> He that humbleth himſelfe ſhall be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted. I wil neuer call him hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that exhibiteth honour to his elders by birth, or equall at the leaſt with him ſelfe. That is a true humilitie or perfecte modeſty, in giuing place to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which be our inferiours. He is
<pb facs="tcp:16492:105" rendition="simple:additions"/> true wyſe, that thinketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe leaſt and laſt of all. For good workes which we haue done by this way onely ſhall bring vnto vs profite, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ How much harme enſueth of Ryottouſneſſe.</head>
               <p>WIlte thou doe thinges worthy of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? haue no reſpect vnto mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine affaires, haue no regard vnto the tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitorious glorie of this lyfe. Seeſt thou other oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied in exceſſe of apparell? haue thou a regarde vnto thy ſoule, howe to decke and ſette it forth with vertues. Laugh ryottouſneſſe to ſcorne: Flee gluttonie and ſuperfluouſneſſe in banketting. As the ſinger chaunteth his notes, ſo muſt
<pb facs="tcp:16492:106"/> not thou cry for delicious din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, but imitate frugalitie. For of ſuperfluitie, what profite or commoditie aryſeth? Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture, thou iudgeſt it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious, to deuour much, to ſwill in wyne till thy belly doe ſtretch, but to a good perſon to much drink is hurtfull. It can not be ſpoken howe much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe hereby happeneth, both to the body and ſoule, as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, adulterie, whordo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, theft, robbery, &amp; murther. Hath the Lord indued thee with aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of treaſure? diſtribute it to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore. Goeſt thou abrode apparelled with ſylke?<note place="margin">Iuuencus. Nemo po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis aeque ſeruire duobus.</note> Haſt thou thy fingers circundited with golde? In the heauens it can not be, that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould take charge of the ſoule, regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the pleaſure and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling
<pb facs="tcp:16492:106" rendition="simple:additions"/> of the body ſo much.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The agréement of the man and the wife, to be very commodious.</head>
               <p>THere riches, there great gaine, redoundeth or doeth multiplie, where the agreement is of the man and his wyfe, yea, ſuch be the bleſſedſt of all other, thoughe their ſubſtance be but ſmal, for they receyue the true pleaſure and liue in the greateſt tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitie of the mind. Therfore by thys fygure <hi>Zelotypia,</hi> the fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of concorde being taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by other wickedneſſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they poſſeſſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryches of <hi>Croeſus,</hi> they were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable of all other creatures. There ſhould aryſe dayly new tumults, brawlings, ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, domeſticall &amp; internall wars,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:107"/> much bitterneſſe, no pleaſure. For this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration I would that they which be ioyned in the bond of Matrimonie, and as it were chained in the ſame, ſhould thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nothing ought to be preferred before concord, being y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roote of all goodneſſe, and ſo to doe all thinges, that peace and tranquillitie might be in one houſe, remayning vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one roufe, and taking reſt in one bedde. This goodneſſe ſhall follow that peace, that in Matrimonie good children, &amp; followers of Vertue ſhall be borne. Alſo the ſeruants and vniuerſall familie, ſhall ſtudie to imitate religion, godlyneſſe, and modeſtie. It ſhall come ſo to paſſe, that by concord of two, the proſperitie of manie things foloweth on euery ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:16492:107" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ Imitation to hoſpitalitie.</head>
               <p>IF a certaine abiect ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. or poore creature, come vnto thee and aſke lodging, receyue him, &amp; if thou haue wherwith to refreſh him, ſet meate before him. This hoſpitalitie or intertainment of thy poore brother, ſhall van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage thee a double gaine. If thou be not ſo welthie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou art able, or at the leaſt wilte not, dryue him not away as a hard harted Saraſin, deſiring ought at thy hands, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering he doth not conſtraine thee by viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but prayeth, beſecheth, &amp; obteſteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. Haſt thou whereby thou mayſt ſuccor the innocent, and aſſiſteſt not him, neyther giueſt ought? Howe wilt thou anſwere, before the
<pb facs="tcp:16492:108"/> face of the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Iudge? by what meanes wilte thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende thy ſelfe? Thou feedeſt daintily, thou conſumeſt more dayly than nede doth require, what damage profereſt thou hir? how much gaine ſuffereſt thou to ſlyde away, &amp; fall from thy handes? Golde being hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp in Towers, waſteth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the ruſt, and is cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away with theeues, when in the meane ſeaſons thy next neighbour periſheth for hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. Doſt thou abound in ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and vſeſt them alone, neyther communicateſt to the nedy, and yet thinkeſt to eſcape the daunger of dampnation? Eaſier ſhall it be for a Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell, to creepe through the eye of a needle, than a rich man to enter into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tabernacle of the
<pb facs="tcp:16492:108" rendition="simple:additions"/> Lorde. Thy nighe and deare brother walketh abrode, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the cloake of miſerie, and thou ſitteſt at home wyth thy banketting diſhes, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing anie regarde to his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treeme neceſſitie, or if he deſire but a ſmall almes, thou canſt not ſpare him a cruſt of breade to eaſe his hunger. He ſitteth naked in the colde, being pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with many a ſharp ſtorm, when thou art clothed wyth rich aray, and paſſeſt by him without all pittie or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Can any man aſſociated with wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked perſons be good?</head>
               <p>Loth alone walked the right way,<note place="margin">Gene. 19.</note> dwelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the wicked mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sodomites. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore yet their ſentence is not
<pb facs="tcp:16492:109"/> true which ſay, that it can not come to paſſe that they ſhould be good, which liue in townes, and among the companie or often aſſemble of men, but ſuch as liue in the wilderneſſe and ſolitarie places. Neyther doe we ſpeake this to the ende we would condemne ſolitarie ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, for it is euident or plaine, that many lyued holily in the wilderneſſe, but we declare to ſuche as be willing to ſpende their tyme honeſtly, that the common cuſtome of men can hinder nothing at all. To a ſlowe and negligent perſon, what auayleth liuing by hym ſelfe: for neyther place, but the mind and maners do good. I would that as <hi>Loth</hi> was, ſo you ſhould exceede one another in vertue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as gliſtering ſparcks,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:109" rendition="simple:additions"/> in the middeſt of a Citie ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, you might drawe the reſt vnto you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The vertues of thoſe which dyed long ſince, to be profitable to vs of this preſent ſtate.</head>
               <p>LEt this alwayes be the deſire of a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let all his endeuouring tende herevnto, that in liuing well, he might leaue a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all memorie of his prayſe, and no vain glorie (as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Poets did in the art of verſifying) behind him, but that he paſſing from hence, his ſucceſſors may haue his diligent conuerſation of life, as a monument &amp; looking glaſſe, dayly to beholde. A good righteous and chaſt man, hath not onely a reſpect, ſeeing the body which he carieth about,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:110"/> is brickle and mortall, to liue in this world, but ſtudy how to profite by examples of vertue, thoſe after his diſceaſe, that be willing to liue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame rate. That euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore might know and vnderſtande, howe much y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good workes of others and like examples might kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle vs to do well, if we be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to follow continencie and chaſtitie, we will bring to your minde a notable exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph the Iſraelite, which bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a yong man of an excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhape or making, as euer na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture framed, had a maruellous conſtancie of chaſte lyuing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes, who in this ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie time of brickle age, would not maruell to ſee the like: Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph being made Prefect ouer <hi>Putiphar</hi> his maſters houſholde,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:110" rendition="simple:additions"/> being a proper yong man, hys Miſtres burnt vehemently in luſt after hym, and when ſhee ſpyed hir tyme, caught hym by the cloake as he paſſed by, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting him to this horrible fact, and wickedneſſe with hir, but he leauing his cloake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde him, fledde from hir pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. &amp;c. O notable ſpectacle to all the whole world. The ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Lambe fel into the handes of the gredie and reuenous Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet eſcaping without hurt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶By the great loue we beare to god, charitie to ariſe towarde our neighbour.</head>
               <p>IAcob ſerued for Rachell ſeauen yeares, counting them for a fewe dayes, bycauſe he loued hir. Heare this O y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ignorant Chriſtian,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:111"/> and moſt vnthankeful toward God. This righteous man that he might obtaine this vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin, diſdayned not to ſuffer all the bitter troubles of a ſhepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdes lyfe, to lie on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ground, to feede with miſerie, deſpiſing raine, winde, colde and ſnowe. How wilt thou then excuſe thy ſelfe, which loueſt not God the giuer of all good giftes, with a like feruent zeale? which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth none other thing of thee, than that thou loue hym with al thy heart. Which thing if thou doe, being mindefull of the word of our lord, thou wilt neuer deſpiſe thy brother.<note place="margin">Math. 23.</note> He that beſtoweth any thing on the leaſt of theſe, beſtoweth it on mee. Thus beſtowing thy almes with a liberall minde vpon the poore, and as it were
<pb facs="tcp:16492:111" rendition="simple:additions"/> laying it in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hand of the Lord, he wil reſtore it vnto thee with a double aduantage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ That almes to be bell, wherevnto other vertues he adioyned.</head>
               <p>WIlte thou profite thy ſelfe? gyue of thy ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the nedy. Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe all the affections of the fleſhe, roote out of thy minde, the inticeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcence, as euill cogitation, anger, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, in whoſe ſtede lette ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues ſuccede.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Many offende by anger and luſt, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they know not the ends of good and euill</head>
               <p>AS God hath gyuen dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſenſes to mannes body, to the vſe of lyfe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie neceſſarie: ſo likewiſe are
<pb facs="tcp:16492:112"/> there attributed various effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule. Of the which reaſon or way of mannes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation doth depend, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning alſo a certaine luſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by the worde of God, to beget children. The affection of anger is giuen to brydle of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences. But what a griefe is it to ſee howe many being igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the fines of good and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, vſed the wicked luſt of their fleſh to puniſh virgins at wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked metings or aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blies. Thei vſe their anger, to hurte thoſe whom they hate. Herevpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it aryſeth, that we runne to great wickedneſſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by likewyſe enſueth ſtrife be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene men, fight &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tention.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The manners and conuerſation of many to be chaunged in tyme.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16492:112" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>WE ſe many, daily in age to repent, that of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, they bee made righteous, of wicked, good, of diſhoneſt, honeſt. I haue ſeene many extorcioners in youth, Dycers (I will not ſay worſſe) which afterward were worthie of prayſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ God is pacified in no other thing, ſo much as in the amending of our manners.</head>
               <p>THe amendement of our behauiour, appeaſeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heauenly power being diſpleaſed with our wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and not Frankincenſe, not ſacrifices, not precious or coſtly giftes, which we ſee ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to corruption. Wilte thou make the anger of God tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, not lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g induring? Ceaſſe
<pb facs="tcp:16492:113"/> from doyng yll. Therefore God doth puniſh thoſe things which we do in this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t life, ſo that we might haue leyſure to repent.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ God is to be loued and feared.</head>
               <p>LEt vs loue God as a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, let vs worſhip him as a Lorde, let vs giue honor to him as a benefactor, and let vs feare him as reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with ſeueritie. We can not be Godly, if we do not loue God, the nouriſher or tender father of our ſoule. Neyther ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he be deſpiſed without dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, vnto whom the Creator of all things, and Lord ouer al men, true &amp; eternall power remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth. He is a father as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which hath miniſtred a birth or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning
<pb facs="tcp:16492:113" rendition="simple:additions"/> to vs, to ſee the light which we enioy. He is God, whoſe gentleneſſe aydeth the vſage of mankinde. He alone nouriſheth vs, he alone feedeth vs. And therfore this to be his houſe in which we dwell, and we to be his familie, we cannot once denie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Fayth is nothing without good workes. <hi>Ex Chriſoſtomo.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THou art learned, thou deſpiſeſt life. What pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth life? Againe, thou careſt for lyfe. For life thou bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſt in fayth, neyther truely canſt thou ſo be ſaued. He that heareth and doth the ſame, him we liken to a wyſe man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ We muſt haue a regard to our brethren.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:16492:114"/>
               <p>IT is the duetie of euery man, to leade as it were by the hand vnto vertue our brother, wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dring through the proneneſſe of ſinne. God him ſelfe for this cauſe taking vpon him our fleſh, entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world. He ſuffered &amp; did many things being a child. To conclude, he tooke death vpon his ſhoulders, that he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deme mankind from ſinne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing giltie of damnation. By the which exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple we muſt reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber to further our neighbor or bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, conſidering he is a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of vs. I pray you is not our brother delyuered out of the chaps of the Diuell, which by any mannes ſounde doctrine, is reduced into the path of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, &amp; doth that which is right, &amp; being riche, beſtoweth much
<pb facs="tcp:16492:114" rendition="simple:additions"/> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the poore? Great, great is hys reward, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by continual ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition and teaching, brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth the ſlouthfull apte vnto vice, into the right way.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ What maner of Wyfe is to be ſought.</head>
               <p>WHat tyme as the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable thirſt, and greadie deſire of coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes, was but of ſmal force, if a yong honeſt man coueted a wyfe, ther was no queſtioning of muche ſubſtance, no reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ryches, ſmall demaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of lande, and ſcarce anie queſtion propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifulneſſe of hir perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but how honeſt ſhee was &amp; ciuill, which ſhuld marrie the foreſaid yong man. But nowe a dayes, we demaund how rich is ſhe, what
<pb facs="tcp:16492:115"/> heritage doeth ſhe loke for, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſaying of <hi>Horace.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Horat.</note> We ſeeke euen to the very ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell of hir backe, as for hir maners that is no matter, that is laſt. A proude Damaſell, a wicked Mayd, if ſhe be riches if ſhe haue coyne, or if ſhe be lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, makes vp our mouth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Why god ſhould the day of death to be vncertaine vnto vs.</head>
               <p>FOr this cauſe god wold that man ſhould be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor at of the tyme of his fate, that he might by a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall ſtudie of vertues, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to watch. He ſayth: <hi>Vigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, quia neſcitis diem neqúe horam.</hi> Watch, bycauſe ye knowe not the tyme and houre. &amp;c. But men do quite contrarie. He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded them to watch, and
<pb facs="tcp:16492:115" rendition="simple:additions"/> they ſleepe downe righte, not practiſing any goodneſſe at al. Therfore they ſlumber in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and watch in vice. What kind of men is this? How ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do we ſee dayly to bolde in wickedneſſe, and ſlowe or tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die in goodneſſe. They die, thei fade away, as well the yong Lambes ſkin as the olde ſhee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. Death is indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, death ſpareth none: yet notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding are we led by this vnto vertue, neyther doe we ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelues to deſpiſe thys preſent eſtate, and couet the eſtate to come.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ We muſt haue a regard to our children.</head>
               <p>YOu Parents, teach your children co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinencie. For the cuſtome of doing euil
<pb facs="tcp:16492:116"/> after that it hath once taken roote, and is of any force, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the trauace of tyme, it can not be wonne by any admonition. Then youth being ledde as it were into captiuitie, ruſheth whyther ſo euer the wicked ſpirite calleth it, and followeth the ſame, willing nothing but pernitious deſtruction, or obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it, onely hauing reſpect of preſent pleaſure, vnmindfull of the torments to come, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the prouerbe. Sweete meate muſt haue ſower ſauſe. Therefore yoke your children in tyme, leaſt they be puniſhed for their ſinnes. It is beſt to reſiſt euilles alwayes aſſaying vs. The medicine is to late pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, when the wounde is to much feſtured. You that haue children, take heede, that they
<pb facs="tcp:16492:116" rendition="simple:additions"/> be vertuouſly brought vp. You Maſters alſo &amp; others, which nourter youth, be it to your charge, and thinke it a great profite or vtilitie, to inſtructe them to liue godly. Teach the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to flee ſinne, exhort the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous exerciſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ To hourd vp treaſure is a daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous thing.</head>
               <p>THou couetous rich man, to leaue much behinde thee, thou hourdeſt vp dayly, thou byeſt ground, thou buildeſt, thou pluckeſt downe, thou choppeſt and chaungeſt foure cornerd ſtones for rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. And that thou mayſt finiſh all this thy gredie deſire, thou pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt and pulleſt from other, thou defraudeſt other, and makeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workeman labour in vaine. If
<pb facs="tcp:16492:117"/> any aſke thee, why thou doeſt thus, ſtreight wayes thou ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt an anſwere, for thy chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens behouf. O blindneſſe, O madneſſe, doeſt thou not ſee theſe ryches to be left as an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for thy children to lyue wickedly? If this age be prone by it ſelfe vnto luſt, to riottouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; other vices, howe much the more then by aboundance of welth doth it runne hedlong vnto the Diuell? Hast thou ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſene fire, as ſone as it hath found out a breach, to iſſue out with ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger flames? So alſo youth is kindled or ſtirred vp to ſinne, by riches the prouoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all euils.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Who be poore &amp; who be rich to God.</head>
               <p>IF thou neuer ſtirreſt, or ſtryueſt to attaine righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, thou art pore,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:117" rendition="simple:additions"/> although a thouſande of thy barnes were filled with grain. He is onely rich vnto God, that is indued with vertue. Wilte thou be acceptable vnto him? Perform goodneſſe and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie. Wilt thou be excellent? Sowe the ſeede of merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Wilte thou be perfecte? Fulfill all the degrees of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that is, abſtaine from wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked workes, euill wordes, &amp; the cogitation of peſtilent things.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ What man is healthfull truly.</head>
               <p>IF thine eyes, thy heade, thy feete, thy ſyde, &amp; thy other members, be in good taking, the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple iudge thee in health. But the Philoſopher ſayth nothing leſſe. If thou be angrie, if thou
<pb facs="tcp:16492:118"/> be puffed vp with pryde, if thou be ſubiecte vnto luſt, if thou burne in concupiſcence, or if thou be couetous. He will ſay that thou art ſounde, if thou bende not thine eyes vpon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mennes goodes. For an enuious perſon waxeth leane or repyneth at an other mans proſperitie. If thou gaſe not vpon riches, if thou luſt not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter an other mans wife, if thou deſire or couet nothing at all, then is there <hi>Mens ſana in corpore ſano.</hi> But thou muſt alſo be hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, pityfull, beneficious, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and hauing a perpetuall peace in thy minde. He that leadeth his life in this race ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſaying of the Philoſopher, he is healthfull, and in euery member perfect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:16492:118" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ The workes of mercy.</head>
               <p>THat man is mercifull in deede, which redeemeth the captiues from their enimies, that viſiteth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore, that cheriſheth the nedie, and ſuffereth them not to lie vnbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, which die in the ſtreates: A pitifull perſon taketh away by violence thoſe that be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed of the mighty, opening his doore to them that want lodging, &amp; defendeth the cauſe of the widdowes &amp; fatherleſſe: He that doth theſe workes, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth vnto God a true and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable ſacrifice.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The comfort of Repentance.</head>
               <p>REpe thy houſe immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, cleare thy breaſt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euery ſpotte, that it may
<pb facs="tcp:16492:119"/> be the Temple of the Lorde, which is not decked with the comelineſſe of gold or Iuorie, but with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> brightneſſe of fayth &amp; chaſtitie. I heare what thou ſayeſt verie well. But I ſay it is a harde thing for a man to liue without ſpotte or blemiſh. Therefore, I counſell thee to flee vnto Repentance, whiche poſſeſſeth not the leaſt place a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vertues. For this is hir correction, that if by chaunce thou offend in worde or deede, by and by repent, confeſſe thou haſt offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, and deſire of God pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for thy ſinnes, which he will not denie for his vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mercie, except thou perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſtill in thine offence, and returne as the Dogge doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to his vomit. Great is the comfort of Repentance. It
<pb facs="tcp:16492:119" rendition="simple:additions"/> healeth our woundes, and our ſinnes, this hope, this porte of ſaluation haue we.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Where, and what Godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is.</head>
               <p>BOdlyneſſe dwelleth in his breaſt which know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which agreeth with his neighbour, which is a frend vnto enimies, whiche loueth all men as his owne brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which knoweth how to brydle his anger, and appeaſe all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furie of his mind, by a quiet meane.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ All wickedneſſes which are done, ſpring of theſe thrée affections, anger, deſire, and luſt.</head>
               <p>ANger is to be cohibited, deſire to be kept vnder, &amp; luſt to be ſubdued, ſo ſhalt
<pb facs="tcp:16492:120"/> thou flee vice. For al things al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt which we vniuſtly and wickedly committe, flowe and proceede from theſe three af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. All the ſtrife of men ſhall be drowned, if the vyole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of anger be ſuppreſſed. Thou ſhalt ſee no man tangled in deceites or readie to miſchiefe. If we keepe vnder gredineſſe or deſire, no man neede be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayde by land or by Sea to be robbed or ſpoyled of hys ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. If euery man endeuour to cohibit luſt, both yong and olde, men and women, ſhall for euer poſſeſſe holyneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Sepulture not to be greatly regarded.</head>
               <p>WHo would not greatly diſalow thoſe that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digaly waſt their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonies,
<pb facs="tcp:16492:120" rendition="simple:additions"/> about ſuperfluous things, building for themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues Sepulchres of Marble ſtone? It ſemeth vnto me true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they burie their goodes in the earth. Neyther do ſuch workes bring any memoriall ſigne or eternity of their name which peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture is ſought. For eyther one Earthquake may ſcatter it abrode, eyther fyre by chaunce conſume it, or hoſtile vyolence ouerwhelme the ſame. But if none of theſe chaunce, verily continuance of tyme ſhall bring it to naught. Deſeruedly therefore a man may reprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thoſe that haue ſo fond a care or regarde. Call not him a wretch that depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in a ſtraunge lande in the wildernes, in an obſcure place or corner, yea what if I ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:16492:121"/> not in his bedde, but that died in his ſinnes. Is he a laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtocke, that dyed farre from his kinne, neither at his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was any friende preſent? Not ſo, though he lacked the honour of buriall. For by the ſame he ſuffered no damage. The ſepulchres of many Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets &amp; Apoſtles be not knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of in the world. Be ſorrowfull, lament and weepe, if thy friend die, not yet wyped from his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquitie. For the death of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners is the worſt. Reioyce if he left the worlde being pure and cleane from all his offences. For precious in the ſight of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord is the death of his ſaints. For they paſſe into a better life, where they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the rewards of their labours.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:16492:121" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ Modeſtie, that faire vertue, to be acceptable vnto God.</head>
               <p>WIlte thou imitate the modeſtie of the Aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient fathers? Looke thou be not preſumptuous, nor high minded: but with mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie giue place vnto other, and couet to be counted an inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, neyther vſe thy ſelfe as an aduerſarie vnto thoſe whiche proffer thee iniurie. Thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing afflicted by reproch, ſeeme not cruel, although he be more ſpightfull that haue ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red thee. Let gentleneſſe and lenitie appeaſe thy wrath. By theſe vertues thou attay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, being deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all bitterneſſe, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant quiet reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:16492:122"/>
               <head>¶ Such as our talke is, ſuch our ſports and bankets ought to be.</head>
               <p>IN al things which thou ſayeſt or doeſt, it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth thee to haue thy minde free from all thoughts, neyther muſte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> be moued by any luſt or feare leaſt a ſparcke of gredineſſe flouthfulneſſe or ignominie appeare in your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication. Likewiſe, ſo vſe thy paſtime and pleaſure, that all petulancie and filthie talke be farre off. We muſt obey the precepts, by the which we are commaunded, that we ſhould neyther reioyce at fonde or ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauld communication. All the actes of Venerie are condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned without wedlocke.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:16492:122" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ An exhortation to mercifulneſſe, mixed with chyding.</head>
               <p>MAny of vs haue money at home, ſuperfluous and ydle, lying by vs. No Euangelicall reading, not Hieremie, not Auguſtine, no lucubrations of ſo many holy Fathers wryting of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of ſuch things, can bring vs to this point, to deſtribute ſome ſmall part of the ſame to our neighbour, labouring with hunger, &amp; waxing ſtiffe wyth colde. O hard, O ſtonie hearts, wyth what eyes ſhall we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſence of the almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Iudge, whoſe commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we haue neglected? God doeth not commaund that we ſhould caſte away our ryches, but vse the ſame. And when
<pb facs="tcp:16492:123"/> we haue ſatiſfied our vſe, then to haue a reſpect vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> poore. The mercifull God hath not beſtowed ryches vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might be kept in our Cheſtes, and Coffers, nay rather there moulde, but that by our abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance the needineſſe of other might be eaſed, and throughly refreſhed. This man waſteth much ryches vpon dyuers and daintie bankettes: this man laſſheth oute ſubſtaunce on gorgious apparell, and thys man waſteth his treaſure at the Table of gluttons, when in the meane ſeaſon one ſicke brother ſtandeth knocking at the gate, &amp; can not be heard, requiring none of all this ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluitie, but wherewith to ſuſtaine his feble nature, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he might liue, &amp; not through
<pb facs="tcp:16492:123" rendition="simple:additions"/> want of foode, ſuffer detriment or periſh. Howe ſhall we, that be not moued with the prayers and teares of our fraternal ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie, looke to be excuſed at the handes of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The glorie of men is not purchaſed, onely of good workes.</head>
               <p>WIlte thou attayne to good works? Se thou doe not anie thing for the fauour of men, but that the ſame eye might prayſe thee which neuer ſleepeth. For if thou couet to be prayſed of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thou makeſt thy ſelfe vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be extolled of the Lord. Both hurteth, both are perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in good worke, if anie man haue a reſpect to humain glorie, and thinketh loftily of him ſelfe. What other I pray
<pb facs="tcp:16492:124"/> thee ſhalt thou be called then a miſerable Miſer. This one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pernitious affection made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Publican worſſe than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie. What ſo euer therefore good workes thou doeſt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaying of Chriſt to his Diſciples in thy minde. When you haue done all that euer you can, ſay we are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſeruants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The couetous man is chidden.</head>
               <p>WHether doeſt thou rage (O couetous man) in hounding vp or gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of treaſure. What greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe leadeth thee forwarde, that thou art neuer ſatiſfied but art cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted none other than a dronken perſon. For as the more Wyne they drinke, the
<pb facs="tcp:16492:124" rendition="simple:additions"/> more they gulge in, &amp; the more dryer they be: ſo thou being ſubiect to the tyrannie of aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, neuer haſt any ſtint at all. <hi>Creſſit amor nummi, quantum ipſa pecunia creſſit:</hi> ſayeth the Poet. The couetous deſyre of mony, increaſeth as much as the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney it ſelfe. The more ryches we haue, the gredier we be. I aſke thee but this one queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. What vtility getteſt thou here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, if thou mighteſt obtaine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole world, being ſure to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the detriment of the ſoule, which couetouſneſſe blindeth, and dayly filleth with all kind of miſchiefe?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ What God requireth in repentance.</head>
               <p>GOD aſketh nothing of vs ſinners, but that we be quiet from ſinne. He
<pb facs="tcp:16492:125"/> calleth for no accompt of that whiche is paſte, if he ſee anie ſpark of Repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance. For this is he which dayly cryeth: I will not the death of a ſinner, but that he turne from his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe &amp; liue. This is he which ſayeth, in the middeſt of thy talke will I ſaye: Beholde I am preſent. (O mercifull God) ſee we be not ſo greedie of our owne ſaluation, as he would y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we ſhuld be ſaued. One thing he requireth, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and being confeſſed, to abſtaine from the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ What maners are to be obſerued in the Church.</head>
               <p>WE muſte remember in the temple of the Lord, to reſtraine from blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous words, vnprofitable
<pb facs="tcp:16492:125" rendition="simple:additions"/> trifles, gigling and daliance, eſpecially, when the Miniſter practiſeth his deuine office. They which abſtain not from theſe things, offend more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe which the lord ſcourged out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Temple. For they ſinne grieuouſly whiche are occupied in the houſe of the Lorde, none other way, than in a place conuenient to ſporte or play. I wyll not ſpeake what wickedneſſe the leud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of men dare committe in moſt ſacred places.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ The prayer of the ſinner conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing in his offences to be vnfruitfull.</head>
               <p>OUr owne ſynnes are the occaſion that we be not heard praying vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. Bicauſe we do wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:126"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:126" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:127"/> and dayly prouoke the lord vnto anger, he will not be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated. For we pray in vaine, if we doe not depart from our ſinnes: We ceaſſe not to bee righteous, or doe any other thing which is contrarie to the worde of God. We make our ſupplications vnto him, and yet we ſwell wyth hatred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt oure neighbour. We would be loued of God, and yet we diſdaine that man which he hath made to his owne ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude or likeneſſe, &amp; which he hath redemed with his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloude. Euery offence ſhall be remitted, if we loue him that hateth vs. Then may we preſeht oure giftes before the Altar. God will not heare vs, except he ſée that charitie grafted which ought to be in
<pb facs="tcp:16492:127" rendition="simple:additions"/> euerie man. That prayer is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo abiect from him, which ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not onely to pleaſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, whether we deſire the health of the body or any other neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie things, alwayes we muſt aſke to this ende, that we may ſpeedely hauing obtayned fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, ſerue our onely ſauiour.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Sluggiſhneſſe is naught.</head>
               <p>LEtte your ſleepe be no longer than nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth: For by conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall ſluggiſhneſſe, the tyme of doing wel is loſt, and we are made more apter vnto vyce: Therefore it was well ſpoken of <hi>Cato.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plus vigila ſemper,<note place="margin">Cato.</note> nec ſomno deditus esto</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuturna quies, vitijs alime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta miniſtrat.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Séeke not more ſluggiſh for to bée</l>
                  <l>than nature doth require:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16492:128"/>
                  <l>For ſleeping much as we do ſée,</l>
                  <l>to vices doth aſpire.</l>
               </q>
               <p>None will iudge, thoſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of a man which ſpende their tyme in ſleeping exerciſe, and being at laſt awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, with their handes vnwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, call for their breakefaſt, &amp; then their dinner, when they haue ſcarce ſleeped out the laſt meales ſuſtenance. Therfore, we muſt watch, pray, ſtudy and labour with tooth and nayle, leaſt we enter into temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, from the which, Lorde be our defender.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ What manner of man he ought to be, that preacheth Ieſus to the people.</head>
               <p>YOu that cry vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple in the Church of god, take diligent heede, that
<pb facs="tcp:16492:128"/> your workes be agreeable to your doctrine. For he that doth as he ſaith, ſhal be called great in the Kingdome of Heauen. Wilt thou reproue other mens offences, ſo that other may not finde the like in thee: Teacheſt thou humilitie? be gentle thy ſelf. Doſt thou exhort vnto pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience? let no anger remaine in thee. Hateſt thou whordom and adulterie? kepe chaſtitie. Teacheſt thou righteouſneſſe? Inueigheſt y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> againſte vices? ſee thou doe no wickedneſſe, couet not a worldely prayſe, boaſt not of thy wytte, but giue God the prayſe, in whome, and by whome we haue pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt ſo great a wiſedome.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:16492:129"/>
               <head>¶ Detraction or backebyting is to be eſchewed.</head>
               <p>WHen any be abſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, thou muſt eyther holde thy peace or ſpeake frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly behinde their backe. For by the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perance of the tongue, it is euident that moſt parte of contentions ariſe. If a good name be better than great ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, he ſinneth greuouſly that detracteth vndeſeruedly the ſame. A backebyter of men is an abhomination. Dauid ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them when he ſayeth: I perſecuted hym that ſlaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his neighbour. If thou happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on ſuch a mannes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, bowe not thine eare to his talke, but turne away thy face, that thou mayeſt learne good, and become a true labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer
<pb facs="tcp:16492:129"/> in the Vineyarde of the Lorde, vnto the which God for hys Sonnes ſake Ieſus, that pure &amp; vnſpotted Lambe, the Redemer of al man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, now and euer vouchſafe to lead vs. Amen.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS. N. Boorman.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <pb facs="tcp:16492:130"/>
            <p>Imprinted <hi>at London by Henrie <hi>Denham, for Thomas</hi>
               </hi> Hacket, and are to be ſolde at hys ſhop in Lumbart ſtreate.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16492:130"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
